<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Manual of devotions collected (chiefly) from the most eminent writers of this age, viz. [brace] the author of the Whole duty of man, Bishop Patrick, Bishop Taylor, Lord Chief Justice Hales, Dr. Lucas, &amp;c. containing certain directions for a devout behaviour at all times, and particularly on Sundays and holidays, and at the time of receiving the Lord's Supper, with suitable prayers and devotions / by a divine of the Church of England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 109 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51853</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24055242</idno>
  <idno type="VID">109636</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248551016</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M541D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42153</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">24055242</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51853)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109636)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1705:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Manual of devotions collected (chiefly) from the most eminent writers of this age, viz. [brace] the author of the Whole duty of man, Bishop Patrick, Bishop Taylor, Lord Chief Justice Hales, Dr. Lucas, &amp;c. containing certain directions for a devout behaviour at all times, and particularly on Sundays and holidays, and at the time of receiving the Lord's Supper, with suitable prayers and devotions / by a divine of the Church of England.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 206 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Nutt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Devotional exercises.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109636:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109636:1"/>
            <p>MANUAL OF DEVOTIONS Collected (chiefly) from the Most eminent Writers of this Age; <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Author of</hi> THE WHOLE DUTY OF MAN,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bishop</hi> PATRICK,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bishop</hi> TAYLOR,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lord Chief Justice</hi>-HALES,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> LUCAS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>CONTAINING Certain DIRECTIONS for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Behaviour at all Times, and particularly on SUNDAYS and HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIDAYS, and at the time of Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the LORD'S SUPPER.</p>
            <p>With Suitable <hi>Prayers and Devotions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Divine of the Church of</hi> ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Nutt,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-hall,</hi> 169<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>▪</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:109636:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109636:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>I Am very sensible that after so many works of this Nature have seen the light, something will be expected to be said for my publication of these Papers.</p>
            <p>The Book is mostly a Collection of Devotions that have been already made publick, by Authors of the greatest repute in this way of Writing: And I hope their Works will be no less their own Defence and Commendation now they are united, than they were before, when pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished by themselves.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain that the Generality of those mean persons, for whose service this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual was Composed, have not all (if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of) those great Authors whence they were taken: And if the Closets of others are furnish'd with them, this large Office of Collects will make them readier at hand on days of more solemn retirement. Not not to mention the convenience of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made by this means the more portable.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:109636:3"/>
            <p>As to the Method of this Book, I have as much right to observe, as many before me, that different methods please different de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout minds. How seasonable some Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects, which make the Original part of it are at this time, and how reasonable and judicious the Collection in general is, must be left to the Reader, upon perusal: Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of Inferiour capacity ought to be thankfull for my Pains, and others have no Injury done them.</p>
            <p>The Book's being Printed obliges no one to be at the trouble of reading or the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of buying it, but gives every body the opportunity of advantage, if there is any thing to be gained by it.</p>
            <p>I should be very glad, if by this labour I may contribute to the making any Persons so serious and sensible of the necessity of a devout Life, in order to fit them for Eternal Happiness, as we all ought to be: And I hope, if they use it with the same mind it was writ with, I shall not fall quite short of this design.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:109636:3"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>EVening Devotions. <hi>Page. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Morning Devotions. <hi>p. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Directions for a devout behaviour at any time of the day. <hi>p. 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Grace in general. <hi>p. 20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Humility. <hi>p. 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer against Pride. <hi>p. 23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Diligence. <hi>p. 27.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Hope. <hi>p. 28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Contentedness. <hi>p. 29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer against Covetousness. <hi>p. 30.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Heavenly mindedness. <hi>p. 32.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Charity. <hi>p. 33.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer against Lust. <hi>p. 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Mortification. <hi>p. 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Temperance. <hi>p. 37.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for a sanctifi'd demeanour under afflictions. <hi>p. 38.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Faith. <hi>p. 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:109636:4"/>
               <item>A Prayer for due preparation for Death. <hi>p. 41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Courage in the profession of Christianity. <hi>p. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for the Love of God. <hi>p. 48.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Divine Wisdom. <hi>p. 50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Meekness. <hi>p. 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer against Wrath and Inordinate Anger. <hi>p. 55.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for an heart to forgive our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. <hi>p. 57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for the fear of God. <hi>p. 61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Conformity to the Image of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus. <hi>p. 62.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Sincerity. <hi>p. 63.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer against Envy. <hi>p. 64.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Watchfullness. <hi>p. 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another Prayer for Charity. <hi>p. 67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for brotherly Love. <hi>p. 70.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for faithfullness and usefullness in our stations. <hi>p. 71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for thankfullness. <hi>p. 73.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for a Sense of God's Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sense. <hi>p. 74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Justice. <hi>p. 75.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Purity of Intention in all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings. <hi>p. 77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Grace to spend our time well <hi>p. 78.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Devotion in Prayer. <hi>p. 80.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:109636:4"/>
               <item>A Prayer for a practicall knowledge of God. <hi>p. 82.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for growth in Grace. <hi>p. 83.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for seriousness and aversion to a Voluptuous life. <hi>p. 86.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for the Cure of a Relapsing tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. <hi>p. 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for frequent and profitable perusual of the Holy Scriptures. <hi>p. 91.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for a pure heart. <hi>p. 92.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for a thorough Conviction of the Malignity of sin. <hi>p. 94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Conviction. <hi>p. 96.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for effectual Repentance, <hi>&amp;c. p. 98.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Sanctification of the Lord's day. <hi>p. 101.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for reverence to Gods house and name. <hi>p. 105.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for the Cure of an aptness to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Gods name. <hi>p. 107.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for an absolute obedience to the Will of God. <hi>p. 108.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Christian Prudence, <hi>&amp;c. p. 111</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for resolute stedfastness to our bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tismal Covenant. <hi>p. 113.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for trust in God. <hi>p. 115.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for the Cure of backwardness to the Holy Communion. <hi>p. 116.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Divine fervour of spirit. <hi>p. 118.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for affiance of Gods spirit. <hi>p. 119.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Perseverance. <hi>p. 120</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:109636:5"/>
               <item>A Prayer for an awakening sense of our Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality. <hi>p. 122.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for the practical Remembrance of the day of Judgment. <hi>p. 126.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for a Practical belief of the joys of Heaven. <hi>p. 130.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for a sanctified fear of Hell. <hi>p. 132.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for a generous Compassion to ones Country, <hi>&amp;c. p. 136.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for discretion in the choice of a Friend. <hi>p. 142.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for faithfullness to a Friend. <hi>p. 143.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Gentleness. <hi>p. 145.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for Patience and Resignation. <hi>p. 146</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for the Contempt of the World. <hi>p. 150.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for a wise zeal. <hi>p. 153.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for the Grace of Gratulation. <hi>p. 155</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for submssion and respect to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours. <hi>p. 164.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for poverty in spirit. <hi>p. 167.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for peace and joy in the Holy Ghost. <hi>p. 168.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for effectual Regeneration and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification. <hi>p. 169.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for the Government of the Senses. <hi>p. 170.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the Government of the Tongue. <hi>p. 172.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pious Ejaculations. <hi>p. 173.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Extraordinary Devotions. <hi>p. 181.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— At home before Church in the morning. <hi>p. 181.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:109636:5"/>
               <item>— At Church in the morning. <hi>p. 183.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— before, at, and after receiving the Lords Supper. <hi>p. 185.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— At home immediately before dinner. <hi>p. 199.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— At home immediately after dinner. <hi>p. 202.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— At Church in the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ternoon. <hi>p. 204.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— At home when come from Church in the afternoon. <hi>p. 204.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Directions for the remaining part of the day. <hi>p. 206.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="resolutions">
            <pb facs="tcp:109636:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109636:6"/>
            <head>Holy Resolutions</head>
            <head type="sub">To be constantly observ'd and kept in mind.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. TO avoid ill company as much as possible.</item>
               <item>2. To Associate with none but men of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and Conscience.</item>
               <item>3. To avoid immoderate Diversions of any kind.</item>
               <item>4. To avoid idle and impertinent talk.</item>
               <item>5. To speak ill of no man.</item>
               <item>6. To do all the good I can.</item>
               <item>7. To pray seven times a day (in publick and private) if possible.</item>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109636:7"/>
               <item>8. To celebrate the Lord's Supper, if possible, every Sunday.</item>
               <item>9. To read the Scriptures daily.</item>
               <item>10. To meditate often on the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chism of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Evening Devotions.</head>
            <p>WHEN I have done with the necessary business of the day, I retire to my Closet or some other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate place, where my Custom first is to read either a Chapter out of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bible, or some other piece of practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Divinity, that my mind may be thereby prepossess'd with good thoughts; and so consequently more intent upon what I am going about.</p>
            <p>Having Pen, Ink, and Paper ready, I proceed to a close Examination of my self with respect to the foregoing day.</p>
            <p>But that I may with better success perform this Duty, I devoutly use the following Prayer.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109636:7"/>
               <head>A Prayer before Examination.</head>
               <p>O Infinite and Eternal Being, before whom all things are naked and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, I am now about to search into a very wicked and deceitfull heart, but must despair of ever knowing the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of my ways, unless assisted by thy holy Spirit: Give me therefore such a portion of it as may enable me right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to understand my duty, and what have been my breaches of it; That I may have such a sight of my Sins as may truly humble me, and make me sensible not only of my danger, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking so great a Majesty; but of my Ingratitude too, by offending so graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a God? O Lord look on the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Christ's sufferings, and for his sake alone hear and answer my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>My Examination.</head>
               <p>I Consider.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1st.</hi> Whether I have this day commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any sin, either in Thought, Word, or Deed.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:109636:8"/>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> Whether I have omitted any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of doing Good.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> Whether I this day received any Signal Deliverance, or Mercy.</p>
               <p>I don't content my self barely with the knowledge of having committed such a sin, or omitted such a duty: but I consider farther the occasion of every sin; and then note down the sin with its particular aggravations, as —</p>
               <p>Whether any Sin committed, or Duty omitted.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1st.</hi> Against knowledge.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> With deliberation.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> Against the Checks of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly.</hi> Frequently, not only once or twice, but often.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>tly.</hi> Against Vows and Resolutions of Amendment.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6thly.</hi> To that degree as to become Customary and Habitual.</p>
               <p>Some Habits are worse than others, as,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1st.</hi> When we are come to a hardness of heart.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> When we go on against any Extraordinary means us'd by God or Man to reclaim us.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:109636:8"/>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> When we become the Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of sin, and endeavour its propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>For my greater ease in performing this duty: I examine but three hours at a time, and reflect on my behaviour during that time; as for instance, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose I rise at six, I consider how I spent my time from six to nine, from nine to twelve; and so for every three hours in a day.</p>
               <p>I am not over scrupulous in my Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, having chiefly a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to my more notorious Crimes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Evening Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Holy Blessed and Glorious Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, three Persons and one God, have mercy upon me a miserable sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>O Lord, I know not what to pray for as I ought. O let thy Spirit help mine Infirmities and enable me to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up a spiritual Sacrifice acceptable unto thee, by Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:109636:9"/>
               <head>A Confession.</head>
               <p>GReat and Holy God, I am an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Creature, and have provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thee, by many and grievous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of Guilt, especially by (<hi>here mention particular sins</hi>) so that had I my just deserts, I must freely own I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve to be eternally excluded thy Favour. But, O Lord hear my Request for the sake of Christ's merits, and pardon all the Transgressions of my thoughts, words, and actions: Give me true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for them, even such as is not to be Repented of? Lord be merciful to me a sinner, deliver me from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wicked habit, which opposeth it self against thy Gospel: O preserve me from all presumptuous wickedness, and cleanse me from my secret faults, supply me with such a measure of thy Spirit, as may make the Words of my mouth the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of my heart, and the whole Conduct of my Life, well pleasing in thy sight, that my Soul may be full of that Divine Peace and Joy which the World can neither give nor take away
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109636:9"/>as long as I am a Pilgrim in this body; and grant that I may be rais'd to a state of Endless Glory at the General Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection, for the sake of thine only Son, and may only Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving.</head>
               <p>O Father of Mercies, and God of all Consolation; I, thy unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, do give thee most humble and hearty thanks for all thy Goodness and loving Kindness, thou hast this day shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, particularly (<hi>here mention par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Mercies</hi>) I bless thee for my Creation, Preservation, and all the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings of this Life: but above all, for thine inestimable Love in the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, by our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, for the means of Grace, and for the hopes of Glory? O let the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of so much Goodness and Mercy lead me to Repentance and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of Life: and grant that I may continue in the same unto my Lifes end, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109636:10"/>
               <head>For Grace.</head>
               <p>O God the Fountain of all Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, who art infinitely pure and holy; I, wretched Creature, who am not able of my self to think a good thought, do humbly beseech thee to assist me with such a portion of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spirit as may enable me to act accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy Will. Grant that I may faithfully discharge my duty to thee, my Neighbour and my self, and in all things approve my self thy faithfull Servant, that at last I may be received into those Heavenly Mansions, where there is Righteousness for evermore: And this I beg for Jesus Christ his sake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>An Intercession.</head>
               <p>THou who art the hope of all the ends of the Earth, hear my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for all mankind, make thy ways known unto them, thy saving health unto all Nations, and grant that where the name of Christ is named, it may be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109636:10"/>honoured by a Conversation answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Light and Profession: Make the Country to which I belong truly Christian; Check that Tide of prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and heresie, which threatens sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Destruction to both our Church and State: Heal our breaches, unite our differences, and settle Peace, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and Righteousness amongst us: Guard the Sacred person of his Majesty K. <hi>William</hi> with Angels: Bless him with a wise and faithfull Council, a Valiant Army, a Long and Peaceable Reign here, and an Everlasting Grown of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hereafter: Pour down all Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Spiritual Blessings on <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi> the Queen <hi>Dowager,</hi> her Royal Highness the Princess <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and all the Royal Family: Make all our Bishops, Priests, and Deacons, burning and shining lights in their several Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred stations, that they may turn ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from the perverseness of the Diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to the Wisdom of the Just, and rejoyce with thy Angels in the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a great number of Souls: Give the Magistrates an hearty abhorrence of the Debauchery and Wickedness of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109636:11"/>Age, and make them vigorous in their endeavours to suppress vice, Bless my nearest and dearest Relations <hi>(here par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularize)</hi> and reward all who have done me good, Pardon and Convert my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Enemies, and work in them, and me, and all mankind, all that good which is necessary to make us accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in thy sight, through Jesus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Preservation.</head>
               <p>O Omnipotent God, on thee I depend every moment of my life. The dangers I am continually exposed to are almost infinite, and were it not for thy wonted Goodness and almighty Power, they had swallow'd me up long before this time, be pleased therefore, most Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, to watch over me this night al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, that I may be protected from all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and refreshed with such moderate sleep and rest, as may enable me to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote thy Glory in that station wherein thou hast placed me, for Christ his sake, my only Saviour and Redeemer.</p>
               <p>Hear me, O Lord, and pardon my failings, deal with me according to my
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109636:11"/>wants, and thy own rich Mercies i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jesus Christ: In whose blessed name and words, I conclude these my Imperfect Prayers. Our Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>While I am undressing my self, I medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the certainty of Death, and of a future Judgment.</p>
               <p>Going into bed, say, I will lay me down in peace, and take my rest, for it is thou, Lord, only that makest me to dwell in safety.</p>
               <p>Being laid in Bed, say,</p>
               <p>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost, three Persons and one God, blessed for evermore.</p>
               <p>If I Chance to wake in the night, I me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on the dangers I am then more immediately exposed to, and of my own insufficiency to help my self, and thereby take occasion to beg for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection from God my only helper in time of need.</p>
               <p>I endeavour to avoid much thoughtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness when in bed, for fear of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my rest, and consequently making
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109636:12"/>me unfit for the Duties of the succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Morning Devotions.</head>
               <p>At my first waking, say,</p>
               <p>GLory be to the Father and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghost, three Persons and one God, blessed for evermore.</p>
               <p>Rising from my Bed, say,</p>
               <p>I laid me down and slept, and rose up again, for the Lord sustained me.</p>
               <p>While Dressing, I meditate on the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Resurrection, and of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Consequences of it to me, if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared.</p>
               <p>As soon as I am decently Dressed, I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain retire to my Closet, or some such convenient place, where I exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</p>
               <p n="1">1. My behaviour since my last nights Examination, and if I find my self to have been Irregular, I add the particulars, by way of postscript to my last nights Account. And then.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I take a review of my last nights Examination, and reflect upon each
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109636:12"/>particular, together with the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of it, that I may more strongly form my Resolutions for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Morning Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Holy, Blessed, and Glorious Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, three Persons and one God, have mercy upon me a miserable sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>O Lord, I know not what to pray for as I ought, O let thy spirit help mine Infirmities and enable me to offer up a spiritual sacrifice acceptable and well pleasing unto thee, by Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Confession.</head>
               <p>GReat and Holy God, I am an unclean Creature, and have provoked thee by many and grievous Instances of guilt, especially by <hi>(here mention par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Sins)</hi> so that had I my Just De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts, I must freely own I deserve to be eternally excluded thy favour: But O Lord hear my Request for the sake of Christ's merits, and pardon all the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109636:13"/>Transgressions of my Thoughts, Words, and Actions: Give me true Repentance for them, even such as is not to be repented of? Lord be merciful to me a sinner, deliver me from every wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed habit, which opposeth it self against thy Gospel; O preserve me from all presumptuous wickedness, and cleanse me from my secret faults, supply me with such a measure of thy spirit, as may make the words of my mouth the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of my heart, and the whole Conduct of my Life well pleasing in thy sight, that my Soul may be full of that Divine Peace and Joy, which the World can neither give nor take away as long as I am a Pilgrim in this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and I may be raised to a state of Endless Glory at the General Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for the merits of thine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Son, and my only Saviour.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving.</head>
               <p>O Father of Mercies, and God of all Consolation, I thy unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant do give thee most humble and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109636:13"/>hearty thanks for all thy Goodness and and loving Kindness thou hast this night shewed me; I laid me down and slept and rose again, for thou sustainedst me, I blessed thee for my Creation, Preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and all the blessings of this Life, but above all for thine inestimable Love in the Redemption of the World by our Lord Jesus Christ, for the means of Grace and for the hopes of Glory: O let the consideration of so much Goodness and Mercy, lead me to Repentance and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life, and grant that I may continue in the same unto my lives end. And this I beg for Jesus Christ his sake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Grace.</head>
               <p>O God the Fountain of all Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, who art infinitely pure and holy: I wretched Creature, who am not able of my self to think a good thought, do humbly beseech thee to assist me with such a portion of thy Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit as may enable me to act accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy Will: Grant that I may faithfully discharge my duty to thee,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109636:14"/>my Neighbour and my self, and in all things approve my self thy Faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that at last I may be received into those heavenly Mansions, where there is Righteousness for evermore, and this I beg for Jesus Christ his sake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>An Intercession.</head>
               <p>O Thou who art the hope of all the ends of the Earth, Hear my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for all mankind, make thy ways known unto them, thy saving health unto all Nations, and grant that where the name of Christ is named, it may be honoured by a Conversation answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to their Light and Profession: Make the Countries to which I belong truly Christian: Check that tide of Prophaneness and Heresie, which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens sudden Destruction to both our Church and State: Heal our Breaches, Unite our Differences; and settle Peace and Concord, and Righteousness amongst us. Guard the Sacred Person of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty K. <hi>William</hi> with Angels: Bless him with a wise and faithful Council: A Valiant Army, a Long, and Peaceable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109636:14"/>Reign here, and an Everlasting Crown in the Kingdom of Glory. Pour down all Temporal and Spiritual Blessings on <hi>Katherine</hi> the Queen <hi>Dowager,</hi> her Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Highness the Princess <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and all the Royal Family: Make all our Bishops, Priests, and Deacons, burning and shining Lights in their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Sacred stations, that they may turn many from the perverseness of the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient, to the Wisdom of the Just, and rejoyce with thy Angels in the Salvation of a great number of Souls. Give the Magistrates a hearty abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Debauchery and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness of the Age, and make them vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous in their endeavours to suppress Vice. Bless my nearest and dearest Relations <hi>(here particularize)</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all who have done me Good: Pardon and Convert my particular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and work I beseech thee in them and me, and all men, all that good which is necessary to make us acceptable in thy sight, though Jesus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:109636:15"/>
               <head>For Preservation.</head>
               <p>Omnipotent God, on thee I depend every moment of my Life, the Dangers I am continually expos'd to are almost infinite, and, were it not for thy wonted Goodness and Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Power, they had swallowed me up long before this time: be pleased most gracious God, still to continue this Care over me, and grant that as I have this day added to my Life, I may be so guided by thy Grace, as to apply my self diligently to do all such good works as thou hast prepared for me to walk in, for Jesus Christ his sake.</p>
               <p>Hear me, O Lord, and Pardon my failings, deal with me according to my wants, and thine own rich mercies in Jesus Christ: In whose Blessed Name and Words I conclude these my imperfect Prayers.</p>
               <p>Our Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:109636:15"/>
               <p>FOr the exercise of my Devotions if possible at five times a Day, in publick and private, besides morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Devotions, I make use of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prayers, collected from the best wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Devotion: repeating at each such time of Prayer as many of them as my zeal and leisure shall point out to me, adding some part of my morning or evening Prayer, and never omiting the Lords Prayer.</p>
               <p>If my bunsiess happens to be so ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent as not to allow me time for such solemn Devotions, I content my self with repeating the Lords Prayer alone, so often as conveniently I can.</p>
               <p>Besides these set times of Prayer, I dart up my Soul to Heaven at divers times of the day, by short and suddain Ejaculations, some of which I have here inserted, being placed immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Prayers. All which pious Eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, I endeavour to detain in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, to be made use of upon any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion.</p>
               <p>This sort of Devotion, I think my self oblig'd at all times to perfarm, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well satisfied that no business, tho
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109636:16"/>never so pressing can excuse me for the neglect of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for Grace in General.</head>
               <p>O Most Gracious God, from whom every good and perfect gift com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, I wretched creature, that am not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of my self so much as to think a▪ good thought, beseech thee to work in me both to Will and to Do according to thy good pleasure. Enlighten my-mind that I may know thee, and let me not be barren or unfruitful in that knowledge; Lord, work in my heart a true Faith, a purifying hope, and an unfeigned Love towards thee; give me a full Trust on thee, Zeal for thee, Reverence of all things that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to thee; make me fearful to offend thee, Thankful for thy mercies, Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble under thy Corrections, Devout in thy Service, and sorrowful for my sins; and grant that in all things I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have my self so, as befits a creature to his Creator, a servant to his Lord; enable me likewise to perform that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109636:16"/>Duty I owe to my self; give me that Meekness, Humility, and Contentedness whereby I may always possess my soul in Patience and Thankfulness; make me diligent in all my duties, watchful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all temptations, perfectly pure and temperate, and so moderate in my most lawfull enjoyments, that they may never become a snare to me; make me also, O Lord, to be so affected towards my neighbour, that I never transgress that royal Law of thine, of Loving him as my self, grant me exactly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all parts of Justice, yielding to all whatsoever by any kind of Right becomes their due, and give me such bowels of mercy and compassion, that I may never fail to do all acts of Charity to all men, whether friends or enemies, according to thy command and example. Finally, I beseech thee, O Lord, to sanctfie me throughout, that my whole spirit, soul and body may be preserved blameless unto the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ; to whom with thee and the Holy Ghost be all honour and glory for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:109636:17"/>
               <head>For Humility.</head>
               <p>O Thou High and Lofty One, that inhabitest Eternity, yet art pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to dwell with the humble spirit, pour into my heart, I beseech thee, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent grace of Humility, which may utterly work out all those vain conceits I have of my self; Lord, convince me powerfully of my own wretchedness, make me to see that I am miserable, and poor, and blind, and naked, and not only dust, but sin; that so in all thy dispensations towards me, I may lay my hand upon my mouth, and heartily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that I am less than the least of thy mercies, and greater than the greatest of thy Judgments. And, O Lord, grant me not only to walk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with my God, but even with Men also, that I may not only submit my self to thy rebukes, but even to those of my fellow Christians, and with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness receive and obey their admonitions. And make me so to behave my self to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all, that I never do any thing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109636:17"/>Though strife and vain-glory; and to that end grant, that in lowliness of mind I may esteem every other Man better than my self, and be willing that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers should esteem them so also: that I neither nourish any high opinion of my self, nor covet one among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but that despising the vain praise of Men, I may seek that praise which cometh from thee only. That so instead of those mean servile Arts I have used to recommend me to the esteem of Men, I may now imploy all my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry and care to approve my self to thee, who resistest the proud, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest grace to the humble: grant this, O Lord, for his sake, who humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self unto the death of the Cross, Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer against Pride.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, merciful and glorious thou art, exalted far above all Heavens: thy Throne, O God, is Glory, and they Scepter is Righteousness: thy Will is Holiness and Wisdom, the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109636:18"/>great Foundation of Empire and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. I adore thy Majesty, and rejoyce in thy Mercy, reverence thy Power, and confess all Glory and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Honour to be thine alone, and theirs to whom thou shalt impart any ray of thy Majesty, or reflection of thy Honour.</p>
               <p>But as for me, I am a Worm and no Man, vile Dust and Ashes, the Son of Corruption, and Heir of Shame and Death. What art thou, O Lord, the great God of Heaven and Earth, the foundation of Holiness, and Perfection infinite. But what am I? so ignorant that I know not what, so poor that I have nothing of my own; so miserable that I am the Heir of Sorrow and Death, and so sinful that I am encompassed with shame and Grief.</p>
               <p>And yet, O my God, I am apt to be proud, proud of my shame, glorying in my sin, boasting my infirmity, for this is all that I have of my own, save only that I have multiplied my miseries by vile actions, every day dishonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the work of thy hands: My under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing is too confident, my affection
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109636:18"/>rebellious, my will refractary and diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, and yet I know thou resistest the proud, and didst cast the morning stars, the Angels, from Heaven into Chains of darkness, when they grew giddy and proud, affecting those bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements which were too high for them.</p>
               <p>Thou, O God, who givest Grace to the Humble, do something also for the proud man: Make me Humble and Obedient; take from me the spirit of Pride and Haughtiness, Ambition and Self-flattery, Confidence and Gayety; Teach me to think well, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound all things fairly of my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to love his worthiness, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in his praises, to execute his errors, to give thee thanks for his Graces, to rejoyce in all the good that he receives and ever to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and speak better things of him than of my self.</p>
               <p>O teach me to love to be conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and little esteem'd, let me be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humbled and heartily asham'd of my Sin and Folly. Teach me to bear Reproaches evenly for I have deserv'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109636:19"/>them; to refuse all Honours done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, because I have not deserv'd them; to return all to thee, for it is thine alone; to suffer reproach thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; to amend my faults speedily, and when I have humbly, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, charitably and diligently served thee, change this habit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the shining garment of Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, my Confusion into Glory, my Folly into perfect Knowledge, my Weakness and Dishonours to the Strength and Beauties of the Sons of God.</p>
               <p>In the mean time use what means thou thinkest fit to conform me to the Image of thy Holy Son, that I may be gentle to others; and severe to my self; that I may sit down in the lowest place, striving to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Brother in nothing but do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him and thee Honour, staying for Glory till thou shalt please in the day of recompence to reflect light from thy face, and admit me to behold thy Glories. Grant this for Jesus Christ's sake, who humbled himself to the shamefull Death of the Cross, and is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109636:19"/>now exalted into Glory; unto him with thee, O Father, be Glory and Praise, for ever and ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Diligence.</head>
               <p>O Lord, who hast in thy Wisdom ordain'd, that Man should be born to labour, suffer me not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist that design of thine, by giving up my self to sloth and idleness, but grant I may so employ my time, and all other Talents that thou hast en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted me with, that I may not fall under the sentence of the slothfull and wicked Servant. Lord, if it be thy Will make me some way usefull to others, that I may not live an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable part of mankind. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, O Lord, let me not be useless to my self, but grant I may give all diligence to make my calling and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection sure. My Soul is beset with many and restless Enemies: O let
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109636:20"/>me not fold my hands to sleep in the midst of so great dangers, but watch and pray that I enter not into Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, enduring hardness as a good Soldier of Jesus Christ, till at the last, from this state of Warfare, thou tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate me to the state of Triumph and Bliss in thy Kingdom through Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Hope.</head>
               <p>O Lord, who art the Hope of all the ends of the Earth, let me never be destitute of a well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hope, nor yet possest with a vain presumption. Suffer me not to think that thou wilt either be reconciled to my Sins, or reject my Repentance, but give me, I beseech thee such a Hope as may be answerable to the only ground of Hope thy promises, and such as may both encourage and enable me to purifie my self from all filthiness both of flesh and spirit, and that so it may indeed become to me an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor of the Soul both sure and sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fast,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109636:20"/>entring even within the Vell, wither the fore-runner is entred for me, even Jesus Christ, my High Priest and Blessed Redeemer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Contentedness.</head>
               <p>O Merciful God, thy Wisdom is infinite to choose, and thy love forward to dispense good things to us. O let me alwayes fully and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely resign my self to thy disposal, have no desires of my own, but a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect satisfaction in thy choices for me, that so in whatsover estate I am, I may be content therein. Lord, grant I may never look with murmuring on my own Condition, nor with envy on other mens. And to that end I beseech thee purge my heart of all co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous affections. O let me never yield up any corner of my Soul to Mammon, but give me such a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of these fading Riches, that whether they encrease or decrease I may never set my heart upon them, but that all my care may be to be rich
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109636:21"/>towards God, to lay up my Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in Heaven, that I may so set my affections on things above, that when Christ, who is my Life shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear I may appear with him in Glory. Grant this, O Lord, for the merits of the same Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer against Covetousness.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, eternal Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of all good things, thou fillest all things living with plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness. Thou clothest the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the field, and feedest the young Ravens that call upon thee: Thou art all-sufficient in thy self, and all-sufficient to us. Let thy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence be my Store-house, thy dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation of Temporal things the limit of my labour, my own necessity the measure of my desire, but never let my desires of this world be greedy, nor my labour Immoderate, nor my care Vexatious and Distracting, but Prudent, Moderate, Holy, Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109636:21"/>to thy Will, the measure thou hast appointed for me.</p>
               <p>Teach me, O God, to despise the World, to labour for the true Riches, to seek to Kingdom of Heaven and its Righteousness, to be content with what thou pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idest, to be in this world like a stranger with affections set up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Heaven, labouring for, and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the Possessions of thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; but never suffer my affections to dwell below, but give me a heart compassionate to the poor, liberal to the needy, open and free in all my Communications, without base designs or unworthy arts of Gain. May my contention be to gain thy favour, to obtain the blessedness of doing good to others, and giving to them that want, and the blessedness of receiving Pardon and Support, Grace and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, Perseverance and Glory from thee, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:109636:22"/>
               <head>For Heavenly mindedness.</head>
               <p>BLessed God, give me Grace to preferr the Interest of my Soul to the World and the flesh, the things Eternal to the things Temporal, that amidst the pleasures of Prosperity and Peace, and the flatteries of Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I may not forget to think what will be the condition of my future state; and yet, amidst the troubles which besiege this mortal Life, I may be supported by the blessed Hopes of a better World, that the Confident belief of the Soul's Immortality may make me industrious, to lay up a good Foundation for the time to come, so that when I shall have put off this Tabernacle of Clay, I may be Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Building of God, not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens all this I beg, thro' Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:109636:22"/>
               <head>For Charity.</head>
               <p>O Holy and Immaculate Jesus, whose first descent was into the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin's Womb, and who dost still love to inhabit only in pure and virgin hearts, I beseech thee send thy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of purity to cleanse me from all filthiness both of flesh and spirit: My body, O Lord, is the Temple of the Holy Ghost. O let me never pollute that Temple with any Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanness: And because out of the Heart proceed evil things that defile a Man, Lord, grant me Grace to keep my heart with all diligence, that no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure or foul thoughts be harboured there; but enable me, I beseech thee, to keep both Body and Soul pure and undefil'd, that so I may glorifie thee, both in Body and Spirit, and be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifi'd in both with thee hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:109636:23"/>
               <head>A Prayer against Lust.</head>
               <p>O Eternal purity, thou art brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the Sun, purer than the Angels, and the Heavens are not clean in thy sight, with mercy look on the frail nature of me, thine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Servant, who am apt to be tempted with every object and to be overcome with every Enemy: I cannot, O God, stand in the day of battle and danger, unless thou cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est me with thy shield, and hidest me under thy Wings. The fiery Darts of the Devil are ready to consume me unless the Dew of thy Grace for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver descend upon me. Thou didst make me after thine Image, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to preserve me so Pure and Spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, Chast and Clean, that my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy might be a Holy Temple, and my Soul a Sanctuary to entertain thy Divine spirit, the spirit of Love and Holiness, and spirit of Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:109636:23"/>
               <p>Reprove in me the spirit of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication and Uncleanness, and fill my Soul with Holy fires, that no strange fire may come into the Temple of my Body, where thou hast chosen to dwell, O cast out all those unclean spirits, which have unhallowed the place where by Holy feet have trod, pardon all my hurtfull thoughts, all my Impurities, that I who am a member of Christ, may not become the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of an Harlot, nor a slave of the Devil, and a Servant of Lust and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy desires. But do thou purifie my Love, and make me seek the things that are above, hating even the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments spotted with the Flesh, never any more grieving thy Holy Spirit by filthy inclinations with foul fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but make my thoughts Holy, my Soul pure, my Body Chast and Health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, my spirit Severe, Devout, and Religious every day more and more, that at the day of our appearing, I may be presented to God washed and cleansed, pure and spotless, by the Blood of the Holy Lamb, thro' Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:109636:24"/>
               <head>For Mortification.</head>
               <p>GLorious God, I see in what a World I live, and what a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy this Soul of mine does dwell in; how little a matter kindles those lusts which blast the Innocence of my Soul, and destroy my Peace: I remember how often I have behav'd my self un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beseeming a Child of God only to gratifie the evil inclinations of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>govern'd Body. Enable me therefore so to mortifie and subdue it, that I may enjoy an entire Peace and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest; so to humble and afflict it, that my self, revenge may bear-witness to my sincere sorrow for all my Misde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours; strengthen me, O my God, to keep my body under, that my dear Soul may not become a cast-away; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie all my corrupt affections, and accept of my Sorrow and my Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, to the atonement of all my sins, thro' the Blood of Chirst.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:109636:24"/>
               <head>For Temperance.</head>
               <p>O Gracious Lord, who hast in thy bounty to mankind afforded us the use of thy good Creatures for our Temporal refreshment. Grant that I may always use this liberty with thankfullness and moderation? O let me never be so enslaved to that Brutish pleasure of Taste, that my Table may become a snare to me, but give me, I beseech the, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect abhorrence of all degrees of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, and let me eat and drink only for those Ends, and according to those measures which thou hast assigned me for Health and not for Luxury. And Lord, grant that my pursuits may be not after the Meat that perisheth, but after that which endureth to Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Life, that hungring and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting after Righteousness, I may be filled with thy Grace here, and thy Glory hereafter, thro' Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:109636:25"/>
               <head>A Prayer for a Sanctifi'd demeanour under Affliction.</head>
               <p>O Just and Holy Lord, who with rebukes, dost Chasten Man for Sin, I desire unfeignedly to humble my self under thy mighty hand, which now lies heavy upon me: I hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge, O Lord, that all I do, all I can suffer is but the due reward of my Deeds, and therefore in the severest afflictions, I must still say, Righteous art thou, O Lord, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right are thy Judgments. But, O lord, I beseech thee, in Judgment remember mercy, and tho' my sins have forc'd thee to strike, yet consider my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and let not thy stripes be more heavy or more lasting than thou seest profitable for my self: Correct me but with the Chastisement of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not with the wounds of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, and though thou take not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy Rod, yet take away thine Anger. Lord, do not abhor my Soul nor cast thy Servant away in displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109636:25"/>but pardon my sin, I beseech thee; and if yet in thy Fatherly wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thou see fit to prolong thy Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, thy blessed Will be done. I cast my self, O Lord at thy feet, do with me mhat thou pleasest, try me as Silver is try'd, so thou bring me out purifi'd; and, Lord, make even my flesh also to subscribe to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signation, that there may be nothing in me that may rebell against thy hand, but that having perfectly supprest all repining thoughts, I may cheerfully drink off this Cup. And how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter soever thou shalt please to make it, Lord let it prove Medicinal and Cure all the Diseases of my Soul, that it may bring forth in me the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fruits of Righteousness, that so these light afflictions, which are but for a moment, may work for me a far more exceeding weight of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, through Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:109636:26"/>
               <head>For Faith.</head>
               <p>O Blessed Lord, whom without Faith it is impossible to please, let thy spirit, I beseech thee, work in me such a Faith as may be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in thy sight, even such as work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by love. O Let me not rest in a dead, ineffectual Faith, but grant that it may be such as may shew it self by my works, that it may be that Victorious Faith which may enable me to overcome the World, and conform me to the Image of that Christ, on whom I believe, that so at the last, I may receive that end of my Faith, even the Salvation of my Soul, by the same Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:109636:26"/>
               <head>A Prayer for due preparation for Death.</head>
               <p>O Eternal and Holy Jesus, who by Death hast overcome Death, and by thy Passion, hast taken out its Sting and made it to become one of the Gates of Heaven, and an entrance to Felicity, have mercy upon me now and at the hour of my death, let thy Grace accompany me all the days of my life, that I may by a Holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation and Habitual performance of my Duty, wait for the coming of our Lord, and be ready to enter with thee at whatsoever hour thou shalt come: Lord, let not my death be in any sense unprovided for, but after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Men having in it nothing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, but an extraordinary Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Manifestation of a great and miraculous mercy. Let my Sense and my Understanding be intire till the last of my days, and Grant that I may die the Death of the Righteous, free
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:109636:27"/>from debt and deadly sin, having f<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> discharged all my obligations of J<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stice, leaving none miserable and u<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> provided in my departure, but<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thou the portion of all my Friend and Relations, and let thy blessin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> descend upon their heads, and abi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> there till they shall meet me in t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Bosom of our Lord: Preserve m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> even in the Communion and Pea<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of the Church, and bless my death<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bed with the opportunity of a Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and Spiritual Guide, with the A<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sistance and Guard of thy Angel<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> with the reception of the Holy S<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament, with patience and a freed or from fondness of my own desires with a strong Faith, and a firm an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> humble Hope, with a just measure of Repentance, and great Treasures o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> love to thee, my God, and of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to all the World, that my Soul in the Arms of the Holy Jesus may be deposited with safety and joy, there to expect the Revelation of thy day, and then to partake of the glories of thy Kingdom, O Eternal and Holy Jesus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:109636:27"/>
               <head>A Prayer for Courage in the Profession of Christianity.</head>
               <p>O Eternal Lord of Heaven and Earth, who art every where, the Rest and Peace, the Refuge and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>urity, the Strength, Help, and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all those who Repose an Holy Trust and Confidence in thee, for nothing, not Death it self can se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate them from thee, I adore thy infinity Love which hath assumed our nature to such a nearness to thy own, and raised the Lord Jesus from the Dead, and given him glory at thy right hand, that all his Faithful Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers might rest assured of thy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal care of them, and they shall never perish, but have Everlasting Life.</p>
               <p>Blessed, Blessed be thy name, for these glad Tidings of great joy, which raises our spirits above this World, and places them in Quietness and Safety amidst all the troubles and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109636:28"/>of this Life: I stand infinite<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> indebted to thee for this Revelatio<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> thou hast made of thy good Will<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Christ Jesus, for the glorious Exa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple he hath set us, who before <hi>P<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tius Pilate</hi> Witnessed a good Confe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, and sealed the Truth with<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Blood, knowing that his Flesh shou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> rest in Hope, and that thou woulde not suffer thy Holy One to see Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. O That I may feel my se<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> enlivened with the same spirit whi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> was in our head, the Captain of o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Salvation, made perfect thro' suffe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ings, being faithfull to him to t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> very Death, and not doubting, I sh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> receive the Crown of Life. It is<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reason I should part with all I ha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> for him, and this Righteousness, w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hath made himself so freely a Sac<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>fice of Inestimable value and effi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for us sinners. O that I cou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> do that cheerfully, which I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound to do in duty, being strengt<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened with all might, according t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> his Glorious power, unto all patien<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> with long suffering and joyfullness g<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving thanks to him who hath ma<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:109636:28"/>us meet to be partakers of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the Saints in light. It is a Faithfull saying, I know that if we be dead with him, we shall also live with him; if we suffer, we shall also reign with him; if we deny him, he will also deny us. Defend me, O God, from so foul a wickedness as the thoughts of denying my Lord and Master and thy Holy Truth: Keep me by thy Power through Faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation, that the tryal of my Faith being much more precious than of Gold that perisheth, tho' it be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Fire, may be found unto praise and Honour, and Glory, at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of Jesus Christ. Settle, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and Strengthen me in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Faith, that a stedfast belief of thy precious promises, a lively Hope in thee through the Resurrection of the Lord Jesus, may not only bear me up with Constancy and Patience under Shame, Reproach, Loss of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Goods, but inspire me with Courage, and an undaunted Resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all dangers, even in Death it self. Fill and greaten my mind with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:109636:29"/>such a powerfull Sense of those im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Joys, that nothing may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear so dreadfull here, as to terrif<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> me from my Duty, or turn me asi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> from the paths of Righteousness, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Truth, and Piety, but suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to thy Will, O God I may commit the keeping of my So<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to thee in well-doing, as unto a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Creator; and endue me, I beseec<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> thee, with such a perfect Love to r<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Lord and Master Christ Jesus, as may cast out all base Fears of suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Fortifie my heart with such a Zealous Affection to his Religion tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> I may not be terrifi'd by any Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, nor afraid of their threats, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be troubled, but sanctifie the Lord God in my Heart, not fearing those that kill the Body, but thee who canst destroy both body and soul in Hell.</p>
               <p>Regard, O Lord, the supplications of thy Servant who here hath made an oblation of himself wholly unto thee, and endue me with a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Prudence, as well as Courage, that I may be as wise as a Serpent and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109636:29"/>as Innocent as a Dove, and never dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour my Religion either by Rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness or by Cowardice, but with a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet zeal cleave unto Truth and Righteousness, saying boldly, <hi>The Lord is my helper, and I will not fear what Man shall do unto me.</hi> In God have I put my trust, therefore shall I never be confounded.</p>
               <p>And what I have requested for my self, I more especially desire of thee for all that now are suffering in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries for Righteousness and the Testimony of a good Conscience. Lord grant that in the very instant that their Sould shall be Rent from their Bodies, when called to seal the Faith with their Blood, they may not only be Martyrs in Body, but also perfect Martyrs in Spirit by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaken Resignation of Spirit, and a flaming Charity to God, and Jesus, Angels, and Saints, through Jesus Christ. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:109636:30"/>
               <head>For the Love of God.</head>
               <p>O Holy and Gracious Lord, who art infinitely excellent in thy self, and infinitely Bountifull and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passionate towards me, I beseech thee, suffer not my heart to be so hardned thro' the deceitfulness of sin, as to resist such Charms of Love, but let the sense of thy Love make deep and lasting Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions on my Soul. Lord thou art pleased to require my heart, and thou only hast right to do it, O let me not be so sacrilegiously unjust as to ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enate any part of it, but enable me to render it up whole and entire to thee. But, O my God, thou seest it is already usurp'd the whole World with its Vanities, hath served it, and like a strong Man arm'd, keeps pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session. O thou who art stronger come upon him, and take this unworthy heart of mine as thine own spoil; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine it with the purifying fire of thy Love, that it may be a fit habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for thy Spirit. Lord if thou seest
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:109636:30"/>it fit, be pleased to let me taste of those joys, those ravishments of thy Love, wherewith thy Saints have been so transported. But if in this I know not what I ask, if I may not chuse my place in thy Kingdom, yet, O Lord, deny me not to drink of thy Cup. Let me have such a since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and degree of Love, as may make me endure any thing for thy sake, such a perfect love as may cast out all fear and sloth too, that nothing may seem to me too grievous to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, or too difficult to do in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to thee, that so expressing my love, by keeping thy Commandments, I may by thy Mercy at last obtain that Crown of life, which thou hast promised to those that love thee, thro' Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:109636:31"/>
               <head>A Prayer for Divine Wisdom.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, who madest the Heaven and the Earth, and all contained therein, by thy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty word, and before whom all Nations are as nothing, less than no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and vanity. How mean then and despicable should that little por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Earth which we enjoy, seem in our Eyes compar'd with thy love and favour, who art the abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Sovereign Lord of all, and canst make thy Servants as happy as thou pleasest? To that very love we owe whatever we have in it, and there is nothing we can hope for, but from the same bounty, which we ought therefore to admire and praise, and love, and cleave unto above all things which we receive from thence, Our daily Experience teaches us the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and uncertainty of all our Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Possessions, and that we our selve<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:109636:31"/>are strangers and sojourners before thee as all our Fathers were. All flesh is grass and all the goodness there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is as the flower of the field. Thou only hast Immortality: With thee is the Fountain of life, and solid Good and Happiness. And therefore, Lord, what wait I for? Truly my Hope is in thee, whose word abideth for ever, and hath made us a promise of Immortal Life with thy self. O pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess my heart with a thorough be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of thy Holy Word; effectually convince me that that is the best Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy and thè noblest Science which dictates such Rules as observed will certainly conduct my Soul to Heaven, and that therefore the Experimental knowledge of a devout and wary Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian is the true and most Angelick Wisdom. Fix my Thoughts and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, on those Eternal Goods, which Christ Jesus hath already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the possession of. Incline my heart unto thy Testimonies and not to Covetousness. Turn away mine Eyes from beholding Vanity, and quicken thou me in thy Ways:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109636:32"/>Cause me to seek for the Learning and Wisdome of an honest Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciple of Jesus as for Silver, and to search for her as for hid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and make me alway to prefer her before an Earthly Scepter, and to esteem Riches as nothing in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrison of her, to love her as the Eye loveth light, to chuse her for my light, because the light that comes from her never goeth out, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer her to Health and Beauty: And since this Wisdom come from none but thee, send her, I beseech thee out of thy Holy Heavens from the Throne of Glories that being present, she may labour with me, that I may know what is pleasing to thee. O may Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom enter into my heart, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge become pleasant to my Soul, that discretion may preserve me and understanding my keep me to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me from the Evil One, and to lead me soberly in my doings. Let not the splendour of any thing in this World: entice me to set my heart too much on Wealth and Dignities and the praise of Creatures, whose
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109636:32"/>breath is in their nostrils, much less to displease thee by drawing back from my duty for the sake of any of them: Settle in me such a high esteem of thy good Will towards me, sill me with such an immoveable love to thee, and fit mine Eyes so strongly on the brightness of that Immortal Glory, which Christ hath brought to light by his Gospel, that it may obscure the most glittering Temptations in this World, and place me out of the reach or out of the danger of them. O make me so wise as not to disquiet my self in vain, heaping up Riches, and not knowing who shall gather them, but to lay up Treasures in Heaven, being rich in Faith and good Works, laying up in store for my self a good Foundation against the time to come, that I may lay hold on Eternal life.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:109636:33"/>
               <head>For Meekness.</head>
               <p>O Blessed Jesus, who wast led as a Sheep to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laughter, let, I beseech thee, that admirable example of meekness quench in me all sparks of Anger and Revenge, and work in me such a gentleness and calmness of spirit, as no provocations may ever be able to disturb. Lord grant I may be so far from offering the least inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that I may never return the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est any otherwise than with Prayers and Kindness: That I who have so many Talents to be forgiven by thee, may never exact pence of my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but that putting on bowels of Mercy, Meekneses, Long-suffering, thy Peace may rule in my Heart, and make it an acceptable Habitation to thee, who art the Prince of Peace, to whom with the Father and Holy Spirit, be all Honour and Glory for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:109636:33"/>
               <head>A Prayer against Wrath and Inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Anger.</head>
               <p>O Almighty Judge of Men and Angels, whose Anger is always the Minister of Justice, slow, but se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, not slightly arising, but falling heavily when it comes. Give to thy Servant a meek and a gently sprit, that I also may be slow to anger and easie to Mercy and Forgiveness. Give me a wise and a constant heart, that I may not be moved with every tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling mistake and inconsiderable acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the Conversation and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of others, never be mov'd to an Intemperate Anger for any inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that is done or suffer'd. Let my Anger ever be upon a Just Cause, measur'd with Moderation or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, express'd with Charity and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, lasting but till it has done some good either upon my self or others.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:109636:34"/>
               <p>Lord let me be ever courteous and easie to be entreated; never let me fall into a peevish or Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous spirit, but follow Peace with all Men, offering forgiveness, inviting them by Courtesies, ready to confess my own errors, apt to make amends and desirous to be reconcil'd. Let no Sickness or cross Accident, no Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment or Weariness make me an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry or ungentle; and discontent or unthankful or uneasie to them that minister to me, but in all things make me like unto the Holy Jesus: Give me the Spirit of a Christian, Charitable, Humble, Merciful, and Meek, Useful and Liberal, Comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with-every Chance, Angry at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but my own sins, and grieving at the sins of Others. That while my Passion obeys my Reason, and my Reason is Religious, and my Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is pure and undefield, managed with Humility, and adorn'd with Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity I may escape thy anger, which I have deserv'd and may dwell in thy Love, and be thy Son and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109636:34"/>for ever, through Jesus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for an Heart to forgive our Enemies.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, in whom we live and move and have our Being; and from whose bounty we receive continually innumerable Blessings, the smallest of which we are unworthy of. All thy Creatures tell us how good thou art, and call upon us to admire thee, to praise thee, to love and serve thee with all our Heart, Soul and Strengh. Thou hast made abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of them more particularly to serve us, and minister to our neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities. And they are all obedient to thy Word, and keep in the order and place wherein thou hast set them. We are the only disorderly Creatures who have wantonly misus'd that liberty thou hast given us, and set up our
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:109636:35"/>Wills above thine, who art the Lord of Heaven and Earth. And yet so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite is thy Mercy, thou hast not chastiz'd our presumption as it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd; but in much Compassion sent thy dear Son with the Declaration of greater Kindness to us than ever. Herein thou hast commended thy love towards us, that while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us, and not only reconciled us when we were Enemies, but purchas'd for us the blessings of Friends and Children, and Heirs of thy Love. O the heighth of they Merciful kindness towards us? O the exceeding riches of thy Grace, wherein thou hast abounded towards us in Christ Jesus? I most thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge it, I rejoyce in thy Love which hath passed by so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny offences: and desire to have such a lasting remembrance of it in my Heart as may bow my Will to thy Obedience, and constrain me to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate thy great Charity in all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Love to thee and to all men. It is the perfection of our nature to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:109636:35"/>be made like to thee in Wisdom and Goodness. And therefore I most heartily profess my self a Disciple of the ever Blessed Jesus, and think it the greatest honour to follow him, the Wisdom and Love of thee, our Heavenly Father, who mercifully heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one that came to apprehend him, and pray'd for his Murtherers, and when he was revil'd, revil'd not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and when he suffer'd threatned not, but committed himself to him that Judgeth Righteously. O that I may so feel the power of his Love, so pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessing my heart that no Enemies, Persecutors, Slanderers, Revilers, or Injurious Persons may be ever able to Conquer my Love towards them: But I may still bear a kind and tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heart to the most enrag'd and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking spirits, blessing those that curse me, praying for those who despite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully use me, returning Courtesies for Affronts and Injuries, bewailing their sins, pitying their miseries, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to overcome Evil with Good. Endue with such a wise, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering and sober spirit that I may
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:109636:36"/>ever prefer the Example of my Lord and Master before all the Customs and Fashions of this World, enduring the mockeries, the shame and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which may be cast upon me for the following his forgiveness and patience. Let no power or opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity tempt me to avenge my self, and to render railing for railing or evil for evil, but contrariwise bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, knowing that I am thereunto call'd, that I should inherit a Blessing. And do thou, O God, to whom Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance belongeth, pardon also and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give those by whom I suffer wrongful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Deal not with them according to their sins, nor reward them according to their iniquities. But spare them good Lord, spare them, and in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy Mercies pass by their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and deny them not the Grace of Repentance, that they may at last be conform'd to our Saviour, ceasing to do evil and learning to do well, and we may altogether be Monuments of thy Mercy, and great Examples of Christian Vertue, and after we have passed our days in peaceableness here,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109636:36"/>live together in Eternal Love and Friendship with our Lord Jesus, to whom be Glory, both now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the fear of God.</head>
               <p>O Glorious Majesty, who art high and to be feared, possess my Soul with a Holy awe and reverence of thee, that I may give the Honour due unto thy Name, and may bear such a respect to all things that relate to thee, that I may never profane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Holy thing, or sacrilegiously in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade what thou hast set apart to thy self, and, O Lord, since thou art a God that wilt not clear the Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, let the dread of thy justice make me tremble to provoke thee in any thing. O let me not so misplace my fear, as to be afraid of a Man that shall die, and of the Son of Man, who shall be made as Grass, and forget the Lord my Maker, but replenish my Soul with that fear of the Lord which is the beginning of Wisdom, which
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109636:37"/>may be as a Bridle to all my Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Appetites, and keep me in a constant Conformity to thy holy will. Hear me, O Lord, I beseech thee, and put this fear in my heart that I may not depart from thee, but with fear and trembling work out my own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Conformity to the Image of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</head>
               <p>O Blessed and Holy Jesus, grant me thy holy spirit that I may lay to heart the Instruction of thy Doctrine, and thy Life, and may not only know, but do thy Will; when I look upon thy Crucifi'd Body on the Cross, may I tremble at the guilt and weight of my sins, which stood in need of so bloody a Sacrifice; and may thy bitter Agonies for me melt me into Love and Passion for thee, and this love constrain me to obey thee: O may I be willing to Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109636:37"/>all my Pleasures to thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; who hast laid down thy life for me. When I am become Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to thy Death, then I may look up with pleasure on thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And Lord grant that the Hope of partaking in it may make me pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie my self and walk as thou hast done in all Meekness and Charity, and Faith, and Hope, that I may be fitted for those Mansions, thou art gone before to prepare for me.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Sincerity.</head>
               <p>O Holy Lord who requirest Truth in the inward parts, I humbly beseech thee to purge me from all Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie and Unsincerity. The heart, O Lord, is deceitfull above all things, and my Heart is deceitfull above all Hearts: O thou who searchest the Hearts and Reins, try me and seek the Ground of my Heart, and suffer not any accursed thing to lurk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:109636:38"/>me, but purifie me even with fire, so thou consume my Dross. O Lord, I cannot deceive thee, but I most most ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily deceive my self; I beseech thee let me not rest in any such deceit; but bring me to a sight and hatred of my most hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Corruptions, that I may not cherish any darling Lust, but make an utter destruction of every <hi>Amalekite.</hi> O suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me not to speak Peace to my self, when there is no Peace; but grant I may judge of my self, as thou judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of me, that I may never be at Peace with my self till I am at per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Peace with thee, and by Purity of Heart be qualifi'd to see thee in thy Kingdom, thro' Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer against Envy.</head>
               <p>O Most Gracious Father, thou spring of an Eternal Charity, who hast so loved Mankind that thou didst open thy Bosom, and send thy Holy Son to convey thy Mercies to us, and thou didst reate Angels and Men that thou mightest have objects, to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:109636:38"/>whom thou mightest communicate thy Goodness: Give me Grace to follow so Glorious a Precedent, that I may never envy the Prosperity of any one, but rejoyce to honour him, whom thou honourest to love him, whom thou lovest, to commend the Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to discern the Precious from the Vile, giving honour to whom ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour belongs, that I may go to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the noblest way of Rejoycing in the good of Others.</p>
               <p>O dear God, never suffer the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil to rub his vilest Leprosie of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy upon me, never let me have the affections of the Desperate and Damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, let it not be ill with me when 'tis well with others. But let thy holy spirit so over-rule me for ever, that I may pity the Afflicted and be Compassionate, and have a fellow feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Brother's sorrows, and that I may as much as I can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his good, and give thee thanks for it and rejoyce with them that do rejoyce, never censuring his actions curstly, nor detracting from his praises spitefully, nor upbraiding his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109636:39"/>Infelicities, but pleased in all things which thou dost or givest, that I may then triumph in the spirit, when thy Kingdom is advanced, when thy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit rules, when thy Church is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted, when thy Saints rejoyce, and when the Devil's Interest is destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, truly loving thee and my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that we may altogether joyn in the Holy Communion of Saints, both here and hereafter, in the measures of Grace and Glory, thro' Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Watchfulness.</head>
               <p>Eternal God, who seest that I walk upon snares and the midst of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, give me the spirit of Fear, Humility, and Watchfullness, that I may walk Circumspectly, passing the time of my sojourning here in Fear. Encompass me with the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of Faith, that I may be able to fight the good fight, to finish my course
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109636:39"/>with joy, and to have confidence at the appearance of my Lord Jesus Christ. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi> Blessed God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for Charity.</head>
               <p>O Most High and Holy one who inhabitest Eternity, I rejoyce to think of the greatness of thy power to protect and assist me; the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of thy Bounty to supply and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me; the greatness of thy Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to guide and Govern me, and the greatness of thy Fatherly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passions to bear with my Weakness, Pardon my Follies, Pity my Miseries, and reward my small sufferings and services for thy sake. I adore thy Incomprehensible Majesty, I ought to love thee the supreme Good and Beauty with the greatest Passion and Vehemence. I can't but say and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily desire, O that I could love thee according to thy Excellent Goodness!
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:109636:40"/>O that I could love thee as thou hast loved us! But alas, I am so far from this heighth of devout affection to thee, that I am some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ready to sigh in much dejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of spirit, and say, O that I did but love thee so well as my self! so well as I do other things! tho' thou justly expectest I should love e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven my Neighbour as my self. I am asham'd of my self and blush to cast mine Eyes towards thee. Only thy great goodness gives me hope, that by thinking of it daily, I shall love thee with all my Heart, and Soul, and Strength, and my Neighbour as my self. Blessed be thy Name, I feel my Soul touched with ardent desire to be more like thee in doing good. And therefore most humbly beseech thee to present thy self continually before me, and to preserve in my mind a lively sense of thy great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in Christ Jesus, whereby I may be powerfully mov'd to put on bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of Mercy, to be tender-hearted, rich in good works, ready to distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:109636:40"/>and willing to Communicate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ability thou hast given me, I desire no greater Treasure than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of this Charity, which beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things, disposing me always to follow after things which make for Peace, and things where with I may edifie Others. Inspire me more and more with this excellent spirit, which never fails, but after it has made me Holy here, will lead me to a state of perfect bliss hereafter, in the Kingdom of love and light, and the Lord Jesus.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:109636:41"/>
               <head>For Brotherly Love.</head>
               <p>O Merciful Lord, who hast made of one Blood and redeemed by one Ransom all Nations of Men, let me never harden my Bowels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any that partake of the same Nature and Redemption with me, but grant me an Universal Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all Men. Give me, O thou Father of Compassions such a Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness and Meltingness of Heart that I may be deeply affected with all the Miseries and Calamities outward or inward of my Brethren, and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keep them in Love: Grant that I may not only seek my own things, but also the things of others. O that this mind may be in us all, which was in the Lord Jesus, that we may love as Brethren, be Pitifull and Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, full of Bowels, and endeavour heartily and vigorously to keep the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109636:41"/>Unity of the spirit in the Bond of Peace, and the God of Grace, Mercy and Peace be with us all.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Faithfullness and Ʋsefullness in our station.</head>
               <p>GOD of Order, Harmony and Love, who hast appointed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Angel and Man their different Stations and Gifts to profit in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Make me, I beseech thee, trusty and diligent and contented in the sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thy Providence has been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to place me. O let not sloth have dominion over me and make my Soul fewel for the Flames of Hell.</p>
               <p>But grant that I may carefully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn my own Soul, and employ all my abilities for their Succour and Relief. O let not an Unchristian self-love possess my heart, but drive out
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:109636:42"/>that accursed spirit, and let thy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of love enter and dwell there, and make me seek not to please my self, but my Neighbour for his Good to Edification, even as Christ plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed not himself. Lord make me a Faithful Steward of all those Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, thou hast committed to me, for the benefit of others, that so when thou shalt call me to give an account of my Stewardship, I may do it with Joy, and not with Grief, and may hear that desirable Sentence, Well done Good and Faithfull Servant, enter now into the Joy of thy Lord, for Jesus Christ his sake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:109636:42"/>
               <head>For Thankfulness.</head>
               <p>O Most Gracious and Bountifull Lord, who fillest all things li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with Good, and expectest no other return but Praise and Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving: Let me, O Lord, never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud thee of that so easie a tribute, but let my heart be ever filled with the sense, and my mouth with the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of thy Mercies. It is a joyfull and pleasant thing to be thankfull! O suffer me not, I beseech thee, to lose my part in that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine pleasure, but grant that as I daily receive blessings from thee, so I may daily from an affectionate and devout heart, offer up thanks to thee, and grant that not only my Lips, but my Life may shew forth thy praise by Consecrating my self to thy service, and walking in Holiness and Righteousness before thee all the days
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:109636:43"/>of my Life, thro' Jesus Christ my Lord and Blessed Saviour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For a sense of God's Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, Infinite and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, thou fillest all things with thy presence, thou art every where by thy Essence and Power; in Heaven by thy Glory; in Holy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by thy Grace and Favour; in the Hearts of thy Servants by thy spirit; in the Consciences of all Men by thy Testimony and Observation of us. Teach me to walk always as in thy presence, to fear thy Majesty, to reverence thy Wisdom and Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niscience, that I may never consent to commit any Indecency in the Eye of my Lord and my Judge, but demean my self with so much Care and Reverence, that my Judge may not be my Accuser, but my Advocate; that expressing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:109636:43"/>the belief of thy presence here by carefull walking, I may feel the effects of it in the participation of Eternal Glory, through Jesus Christ.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Justice.</head>
               <p>O Thou King of Righteousness, who hast Commanded us to keep Judgment and do Justice, be pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thy Grace to cleanse my Heart and Hands from all fraud and Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, and give me a perfect Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and Uprightness in all my deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. O make me ever abhor to use my power to oppress, or my skill to deceive my Brother, and grant I may most strictly observe that sacred rule of doing as I would be done to, that I may not dishonour my Christian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession by an unjust and fraudulent life, but in Simplicity and Godly Sincerity,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:109636:44"/>have my Conversation in the World, never seeking to heap up Treasures in this Life, but preferring a little with Righteousness before great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues without Right. Lord make me exactly carefull to render to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man what by any sort of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation becomes his due, that I may never break the Bond of any of those Relations that thou hast placed me in, but may so behave my self to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all, that none may have any evil thing to say of me, that so, if it be possible, I may have Peace with all Men; or however, I may by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Innocency and taking heed to the thing that is Right, have Peace at the last, even Peace with thee, thro' Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:109636:44"/>
               <head>For Purity of Intention in all Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, who hast made all things for Man, and Man for thy Glory, Sanctifie my Body and Soul, my Thoughts and my Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, my Words and Actions, that whatsoever I shall think or speak, or do, may by me be designed to the Glorification of thy Name, and by thy Blessing, it may be effectual and successfull in the Work of God accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it can be capable. Lord, turn Necessities into Vertues, the Works of Nature into the Works of Grace, by making them Orderly, Regular and Temperate, Subordinate and Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to Ends beyond their own proper efficacy, and let no Pride or Self-secking, no Covetousness or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, no Impure Mixture or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handsom Purposes, no little Ends and low Imaginations pollute my spirit, and unhallow any of my Words and Actions: But let my Body be a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109636:45"/>of my Spirit, and both Body and Spirit Servants of Jesus, that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things for thy Glory, here I may be a partaker of thy Glory hereafter, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Grace to spend our Time well.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God, who from all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity dost behold and love thine own Glories and Perfections infinite, and hast Created me to do the work of God, after the manner of Men, and to serve thee in this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, according to my Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Give me Grace that I may be a Curious and Prudent spender of my Time, so as I may best prevent or resist all Temptation, and be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Christian Commonwealth, and by discharging all my Duty, may
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:109636:45"/>Glorifie thy Name. Take from me all slothfullness, and give me a Diligent and Active Spirit and Wisdom to choose my Employment, that I may do works proportionable to my Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and to the Dignity of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, and may fill up all the spaces of my time with Actions of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Charity, that when the Devil assaults me, he may not find me idle, and my dearest Lord at his sudden coming, may find me busie in Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Necessary, and Pious Actions, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving my Talent, entrusted to me by thee, my Lord, that I may enter into the Joy of my Lord, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of his Eternal Felicities, even for thy Mercies sake, and for my dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Saviour's sake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:109636:46"/>
               <head>For Devotion in Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Gracious Lord God, who not only permittest but invitest us miserable and needy Creatures to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sout our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etitions to thee; Grant, I beseech thee, that the frequency of my Prayers may be somewhat an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to those continual needs I have of thy Mercy. Lord, I confess, it is the greatest Honour and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Advantage thus to be allowed access to thee. Yet so sottish and stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid is my prophane heart, that it shuns or frustrates the opportunities of it. My Soul, O Lord, is posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with a Spirit of Infirmity, 'tis bow'd together, and can in no wise lift up it self to thee. O, be thou pleased to cure this sad, this mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Disease, to enspirit and enli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this earthly, drowsie Heart, that it may freely mount towards thee,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:109636:46"/>that I may set a true value on this most valuable privilege, and take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in approaching to thee, and that my approaches may be with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, some way answerable to that awfull Majesty, I come before, with an Importunity and Earnestness answerable to those pressing Wants I have to be supplied, and with such a fixedness and attention of mind as no wandering Thoughts may inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, that I may no more incur the Guilt of drawing near to thee with my Lips when my Heart is far from thee, or have my Prayers turn'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sin, but may so ask that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, seek that I may find, and knock that it may be open'd to me, that from Praying to thee here, I may be translated to the praising thee Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in thy Glory, thro' the Merits and Intercession of Jesus Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:109636:47"/>
               <head>For a Practical Knowledge of God.</head>
               <p>GLorious God, let my knowledge of thy Nature teach me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny all Iniquity, and to be holy as thou art holy: Let thy Goodness make me love thee, and thy Power and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice make me fear thee, and let both wing my Devotion and damp my Lusts: Let thy Truth and thy Power beget in me a perfect affiance in thee. Let thy Wisdom and thy Love per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade me to submit quietly to thy Will, and give me such a sense of thy Omnipresence, as may oblige me always to walk before an Almighty God, and be perfect till I enter at last into thy immediate presence and unspeakable Joys in the Life to come, thro' Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:109636:47"/>
               <head>For growth in Grace.</head>
               <p>O Thou Divine Fountain and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penser, thou Author and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisher of every good and perfect Gift, perfect, I beseech thee, that good work of Grace, which thou hast be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in me, and carry it on to a full Growth and Maturity: Assist me, O Holy Inspirer so constantly from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove that I may be always in my Thoughts and Affections there, that whatever good Thoughts are at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Time suggested to my mind may spring up into fix'd principles, and all my Heavenly desires, may become a New Nature, the constant Tenour and Temper of my spirit, and all my Holy Purposes and Resolutions may advance into a constant practice and zealous exercise of Godliness, and all my pious actions may improve in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:109636:48"/>to confirmed Habits, and become daily more and more free, chearfull, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous and delightsome: O may my Religious motion and progress in Holiness, manifest the Sincerity of Grace within me, and that I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed alive unto God and quickened by thy spirit. I am part of thy Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, O grant that like a flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing Tree planted by the Rivers of Water, I may alway bring forth such good fruit as thou expectest in due Season. O never suffer me to be like a Tree without fruit twice dead pluckt up by the Roots, whose end is to be burnt: Never suffer my leaf of Holy Profession to fall, or my good fruit to wither, but grant that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Pious work that I take in hand may prosper. Grant that the more I advance in Years, the greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress I may make in Grace, that I may bring forth much fruit of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness in my mature Age, and may then be chiefly fat, and well liking as to my Improvement in Holiness. O Blessed Lord give me to become
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:109636:48"/>thus more and more like thee, a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker in a larger measure of thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature and Excellencies. Give me to hunger and thirst after Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, that I may in a higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree be satisfi'd therewith. Give me to lay up for my self Treasures of Grace for Heaven rather than Treasures of Mammon for Earth; to multiply and encrease my spiritual Talents; to grow rich in Faith and good Works; to rise up to a fullness of Stature in Christ Jesus; to walk worthy of thee, our God, to all well pleasing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting Holiness in thy fear; to be filled with all the fruits of thy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which accompany Salvation, that these things being in me, and abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, an entrance may be administred unto me into the Everlasting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. <hi>Amen.</hi> Blessed Saviour for thy Cross and Passion's sake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:109636:49"/>
               <head>For Seriousness and Aversion to a Voluptuous Life, and Vain, Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, Ʋnlawfull, sensual Mirth.</head>
               <p>LORD, who knowest what great things my Soul is capable of, wean me from the false embraces of this Evil World, turn all these sinfull Joys to bitter and wholesome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections in me: Make me to see the Foulness and Deformity, the Empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Vanity, the Shortness and Uncertainty, the Falshood and Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and the Weariness, Unsatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingness and Misery of the Mirth of Carnal and Impenitent Men. O let my Heart be fill'd, let my Soul be ravished with those transcendent Joys of thine which are for ever; Give me a Joyfull Soul to rest securely in them, and a ready Heart, devoutly thankfull for them. Lord, moderate my desires to outward Enjoyments;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:109636:49"/>let me relish no sweetness but in thy Love, no Goodness but in thy Grace, no Comfort but in the full assurance of thy Glory. Forgive those wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hours, which have been stoln from thy Service: O Lord, my God, I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily bewail them, and willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve to spend my days in sorrow for them. Make me more watchfull over my corrupt Heart, more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of my precious Time, more se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in the weighty work of my Salvation, more sorrowful for Sin, more mindfull of Infinite Eternity, of the hour of Death, and the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that so I may affect the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of this Life soberly, use them sparingly, and leave them chearfully.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:109636:50"/>
               <head>For the Cure of a Relapsing Temper, and that Despair which has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten been occasioned by it.</head>
               <p>BLessed Lord, wilt thou accept of such a sinfull Creature as I am, to appear before thee, to approach to thee, and to sue to thee for Mercy? How bold am I to look upon thee with these Adulterous Eyes, that have so been gazing on unlawfull objects? How much presuming on thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to implore thee with that Tongue that hath so much provok'd thy Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure? How Impudent to offer that dis-loyal heart to thee, that hath been wedded so fast to a sinful World? Lord, when my own Wretchedness, had brought thy gracious Visitation on me, when thy hand pressed me sore, when thine Arrows stuck fast in me, and the Venom of them drunk up my spirits, when my heart was in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:109636:50"/>heaviness, and my Soul in bitterness, when mine own Conscience pleaded powerfully against me, and the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of a second Death were ready to devour me, I then earnestly implor'd thee for Mercy and thou freely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gavest me. I then begg'd my life of thee, that I might thankfully devote the Remnant of my life to thee? Ah, Lord, how wretchedly hath my own heart deceived me? What serious rows and faithfull promises did I then make unto thee? and yet how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly, how foolishly am I departed from thee? How vainly have I tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled out that precious Time that thou hast given me? How justly maist thou deprive me of this wretched life, by which I have so much dishonoured thee? And now, Lord, when I have even wearied out my self in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, when my Soul is overcharged with sin, and my heart with sorrow, when the vanity of this Life is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to forsake me, and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left but misery and shame to seize me, I have not yet resolv'd se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:109636:51"/>to come unto thee. Lord leave me not unto the weakness o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> my own Infirmities, expose me not to the raging billows of my strong Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: Lord, let not the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my horrible Relapses, make me desperately wallow in the Mire, or devote my Soul to Hell, as an irrecoverable Prey; suffer me not to sink into this depth of sin, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy'd by this dreadfull storm of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and mine own accusing Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; Rebuke these Winds and Waters, and cause a Blessed Calm within me, reach out thy hand of Mercy, and support me, strengthen my drooping Soul, that I may Joyfully and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully lay hold upon thee, give me a fix'd heart that I may return to thee in good earnest, and may this very hour be graciously accepted of thee: O Pardon, Pardon! Sanctifie, Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie! Recover, recover me before I go hence, and can no longer address thee but in vain, for the sake of the most Noble, Gracious, and Excellent Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:109636:51"/>
               <head>For the Frequent and Profitable peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal of Holy Scripture.</head>
               <p>SO Sanctifie my sinfull Soul, O Lord, that I may gladly dedicate some part of my Time to the reading some portion of thy Sacred Scriptures. O let them ever be the Joy of my Joy, the Life of my Life, the Light of mine Eyes, and the Comfort and Stay of my Heart: Give me an humble Soul that I may read thy Holy Lines, with Holy fear and awful reverence, that I may be both happily inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and refreshed by it. Give me a discerning Soul, that I may see the Wonderfull things of thy Law, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love it, and delight in it, that my Heart may be enflam'd by it, and my lips be ever talking of it. O let thy Statutes be my Song in the House of my Pilgrimage, that I may walk in thy ways with Constancy, and run in
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:109636:52"/>thy Race with fervency, for Ch<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> his sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For a Pure heart.</head>
               <p>GLorious God, when I consider ho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> evidently impure I am in my own Eyes, and in the best of my Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance: How loathsome must I needs appear in thy sight, who art Purity it self, and canst not behold Iniquity. Blessed Lord, as thou hast given me the light of thy Word to discover me to my self, so give me also the Sword of thy spirit to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from my self: Deliver me, O Lord, from the Old and Evil Man, from mine own secret. Corruptions, from my known and unknown Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations. Search my Heart, O Lord, and try my Heart? O let no
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:109636:52"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ase and by-respects inhabit there, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o rob thee of thine Honour, no false <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd vain Intentions to cheat me of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y present Holiness and future Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness. Pardon and pass by the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and unknown errors of my sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full life, the great disturbances of my corrupt Affections, although they many times prevail against me, yet <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>et thy saving Grace, Lord, be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for me. Lord, make me pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y and entirely Holy, neither barely for fear of thy Punishments, nor for Hope of thy Rewards, but for thy sake only, O my God, who art Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness it self. <hi>Amen,</hi> for Christ his sake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:109636:53"/>
               <head>For a thorough Conviction of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of Sin.</head>
               <p>O Thou Immaculate Purity, thou perfectly Holy and Righteous Divine Being, who hast manifested thy Love to Holiness, and thy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred against all impiety, chiefly in sending thy Son into the World by his pure Example, and by his Holy Doctrine to destroy the sinfull works of the Devil, and to promote a life of uprightness. O form, I beseech thee, those Excellent Graces which shone so brightly in our Saviour, in my inmost and outward Man. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me not only from the Guilt and Punishment, but from the Pollution and Prevalency of it. Preserve me in the World from the approbation of Vice, and the Corruptions of the World.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:109636:53"/>
               <p>Give me to behold more of the Malignant Nature of Sin, and the Turpitude, Folly, Baseness, and Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude thereof, and then I shall the more thoroughly Grieve, detest and resolve on the abandoning of it. Convince me deeply, Gracious God, that Sin is the greatest of Evils, and then I shall betake my self to thee, the greatest of Goods: Make me sensible of my Natural Incapacity of seeing thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Holiness, which is opposite to this Monster Sin, that I may not ruin my self by a false security and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption whilst at Peace with it, and abuse thy Goodness, and Prostitute the Meritorious Blood of Christ by making it a Sanctuary of refuge for Sin, which was intended such only for the Refuge of the Sinner upon his Sincere and hearty Conversion and Repentance. Lord, I am blind and poor and naked; blind as to the true saving knowledge, which work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by Love; poor and naked as to any inherent acceptable Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:109636:54"/>of my own. O Cloath me with the Robes of thy perfect imputed Righteousness. Let my life be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual endeavour of subduing in my self the love of Sin, of becoming enamour'd with the Beauty of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and every way such as thou wouldst have me to be, for Christ his sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Contrition.</head>
               <p>O Holy Lord, who art a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Embracer of true Penitents, but yet a consuming fire towards ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinate Sinners? How shall I approach thee, who have so many provoking sins to enflame thy Wrath, and so little Sincere Repentance to encline thy Mercy. O be thou pleased so to soften and melt this hard and obdurate heart
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:109636:54"/>of mine, that I may heartily bewail the Iniquities of my life. Strike this Rock, O Lord, that the Waters may flow out, even floods of Tears to wash my polluted Conscience. My drowsie Soul hath too long stept securely in Sin, Lord, awake it, tho' it be with Thunder, and let me rather feel thy Terrors than not feel my Sin. Thou sentest thy Blessed Son to heal the broken-hearted: But, Lord, what will that avail me if my heart be whole? O break it that it may be capable of this healing Vertue. Grant, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee, that having once tasted the bitterness of Sin: I may fly from it as from the Face of a Serpent, and bring forth fruits of Repentance and Amendment of life, to the praise and glory of thy Grace in Jesus Christ our blessed Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:109636:55"/>
               <head>A Prayer for effectual and undelay'd Repentance to our selves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</head>
               <p>MOst Mercifull Father, Patient and Long-suffering, who wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est to be gracious, and yet whose spirit will not always be striving with obstinate impenitent Sinners; Dost thou, O Lord, call unto us; Behold now is the accepted time, behold now is the day of Salvation, and do we cry, To morrow is soon enough; some days or years hence will be as accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table as this present one? A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that we are, Ah Foolish Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Creatures, who shall know best the day of our Salvation? Thou our God the Author of it, or we? Who should know best how long thy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit will strive with us, how long thou wilt wait to be gracious? O cause me to day, whilst 'tis call'd to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:109636:55"/>day, to hear thy voice and not hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en my Heart against thy Invitation to Repent. Convince us, Blessed Lord, in order to a present Amendment, that 'tis some degree of hardning our hearts not to hearken to thy voice to day, that every continuance in sin is one advance more towards fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Impenitence, a rendring our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Conversion the more grievous and difficult, and our Confirmation in Wickedness, the greater and nearer to irretrievable; and in a sense of all this, make us, we beseech thee, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire out of the ways of Iniquity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately. O cause us to give all diligence at present to make our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Election sure, to work the Religious work, for which we were sent into this World, while 'tis day before the night of Death come, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 'tis impossible to work our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Who can tell what a day may bring forth? Cause us therefore, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God, to live every day as if it were to be our last, for that we know not but it may be such. Cause us
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:109636:56"/>to live so at present as we shall wish we had done when we come to die. O grant we may not die with any guilt upon our Consciences, or any known sin unrepented of. Grant that we may not put far from us the evil day, and thereby flatter our selves in a state of Impenitence and Endless Destruction; but give us Grace to use well the means of Grace and improve the opportunity of Salvation while they are mercifully offered us, lest we provoke thee, our God, to swear in thy Wrath, that such obstinate sinners should never enter into thy Rest. Let, Holy Father, the Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the time of our Saviour's coming to Judgment, either to the Universal one, or that of each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Person soon after his Death, make every one of us live in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual readiness and preparation for it, that we may not have our Oyl of Grace to seek, our Lamp of an Holy Conversation to trim and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenish when we shall enter in with the Bridegr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om of our Souls, Christ
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:109636:56"/>Jesus, into his Marriage Feast: But grant that at what season soever our Lord comes to call us to an account of the Talents committed to our Trust, he may behold all our debts to his Divine Justice ready cancell'd by our Repentance, through the merits of his Blood, and finding us persever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly employ'd in Good Works, he may say unto us, Well done Good and Faithfull Servants, Enter into your Master's Joy. <hi>Amen.</hi> Blessed Jesus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Habitual Sanctification of the Lords day, and a Reverent use of the Ordinances of Salvation.</head>
               <p>BLessed and Glorious Lord God, thou Lord and Instituter of the Sabbath, who allowest us six days in seven for our Temporal and Wordly concerns, and hast set apart
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:109636:57"/>a seventh only for thine own especial service? O how wisely hash thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for both our Souls and Bodies? For how wou'd our outward Man want Food and Raiment, were not days of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour afforded it, wherein by honest Industry those necessaries are procur'd, and how would our spirits pine away and languish as to all Gracious endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, were not seasons appropriated to thy Divine Worship. O that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at present we may rest at such seasons from the Works of sin as well as from those of our particular Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: O that we may always be in the spirit on thine own day, that we may worship thee thereon in Spirit and in Truth, that we may keep it so Holy and Sanctifi'd unto thee as that it may be a Pledge and Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest of an Eternal Sabbatism with thee in Light and Glory: 'Tis the day which the Lord hath made by his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifying Resurrection. O may I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways rejoyce and be glad thereon with a holy rejoycing. 'Tis the day which was the Birth-day of our Hopes
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:109636:57"/>and future Blessed Expectations: O may it ever be a day of improvement in Grace, of Holy Ardours and Devout Enravishments; grant gracious Father that I may never find my own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, or speak my own words, or do mine own deeds on thine hallowed day, but may both call and esteem it a Delight, holy of the Lord, honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? O that Heaven by a Heavenly frame and temper of spirit may be begun in me here by means of my pious Intercourses with Heaven, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midst the duties of thy day? When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I am going, O Lord, unto thy house of Prayer, the place where thine Honour dwells, O Pardon me that I am not prepar'd according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of thy sanctuary, and make me to consider that the place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I am to stand is Holy Ground. O do thou our God vouchsafe to go along with me into thy Temple by the Holy Aids and Assistances of thy Spirit. Cause me to approach thee there with Reverence and to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship before thee with a zealous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:109636:58"/>When I meditate, let me do it with all Seriousness, Heavenly Mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness and Edification; when I pray let it be with the utmost Attention, Faith and holy fervour; when I hear the glad Tidings of thy Gospel may it be with all diligent and hearty at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on thy Word and Doctrine; when I read thy Holy Scriptures, may they make me wise unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; may I read them with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, with an Affectionate Gust and Relish, with a Reforming and inward Digestion of them into spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Grace and Nourishment; when I receive the Communion may it be for the better, and not for the worse; may the broken bread be Christ's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the pour'd Wine his Blood, and both an entire Jesus, Wisdom, Righteousness and Redemption to my Soul. Hear me for his merits sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:109636:58"/>
               <head>For Reverence to God's House and Name.</head>
               <p>GReat and Incomprehensible God, strike such an awe, I beseech thee, in my heart that I may hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Reverence thee in thy Name, which is Great, Wonderful, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and carry such a wonderfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to thy house, and all things that relate to thee and thy Worship, as may express our Reverence to thy Great Majesty. And since thy Glory is the great end of all thy Works: I desire it may be the beginning and end of all my Services. Let thy great Name be Glorious and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and Sanctified throughout all the World: Let the knowledge of thee fill the Earth as the Waters cover the Sea. In all the dispensations of thy Providence enable me to see
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:109636:59"/>thee, and to sanctifie thy Name in my Heart with Thankfullness, in my Lips with Thanksgiving, and in my Life with Dutifullness and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. O may I and all mankind have high and honourable Thoughts touching thee in some measure suita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thy Glory, Majesty, Goodness, Wisdom, Bounty, and Purity; and may we in all our Words and Actions, manifest these inward apprehensions with suitable and becoming Words, and Actions. This I beg for the sake of Jesus.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:109636:59"/>
               <head>A Prayer for the Cure of an Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitual aptness to profane God's Name.</head>
               <p>GReat and Dreadfull God, thou hast declared, <hi>That thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not hold him guiltless that taketh thy name in vain:</hi> O Pardon, I beseech thee, all my past profanations of thy Sacred Name, and my present apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to use it rashly and on light occasions, notwithstanding my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to conquer this grievous and evil habit: Set a Watch, O my God, over my unruly Tongue thus set on fire of Hell, and keep the door of my ungratefull Lips that have dar'd to Blaspheme that Glorious and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Being which made, and desires to deliver me: Deliver me, Deliver me, I earnestly entreat thee from the slavish Custom of such monstrous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude. Give me an awfull sense
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:109636:60"/>of thy Name, lest the common use of it in Trivial Assertions, or the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal abuse of it in lifeless Devotion, betray me at length to a bolder forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullness of thee, by the horrible Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of Perjury. Hear me for the sake of thy beloved Son Jesus Christ.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Absolute Obedience and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission to the Will of God.</head>
               <p>HOly Father, since thy Will is most Holy, Righteous and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, Just and Wise, let it be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more our choice to make thy Will to be ours, and to resign up our Wills unto thee and to thy Will. Let the Will of thy Counsels be done, and altho' we know it is not in the Power of Men or Devils to hinder it, yet so we do testifie our duty to thee in praying that nothing may hinder or retard the Will of thy.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:109636:60"/>Counsels, for thy Counsels are full of Wisdom, Benignity, and Purity, and Righteousness, and we beg thee to give us hearts most entirely to wait upon thee in whatsoever thou shalt appoint concerning us, that if thou shalt give us Prosperity and Success in this life, we may receive it with all Thankfullness and Humility, and use it with Sobriety, Moderation, and Faithfullness; if thou shalt send us Adversity we may entertain it with all Submissiveness, Patience, Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness, and Chearfullness, submitting to the Dispensation to our Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, ever acknowledging thy Will to be the best Will, and that whereunto it becomes us with all Humility to submit; and in the midst of all to rejoyce that our Portion and Patrimony, and Happiness is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served for us in another Life. And as we desire the Will of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels may be done upon us, so we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire the Will of thy Commands may be done by us and by all mankind, that we may conform our Hearts and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:109636:61"/>Lives to the Rule of thy Blessed Word, that we may live in all Piety to thee, our God, in all Righteousness to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, in all Sobriety towards our selves, that we may follow those Precepts and Patterns of Holiness, Righteousness, Justice, Patience, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, Goodness, Charity, and all other Moral and Christian Vertues that thou hast in thy Word Commanded or Propounded for our Practice and Imitation. And that this Obedience unto thee may be performed by me and all mankind in some measure an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to what is done by thy Glorious Angels in Heaven, that we may do it chearfully without mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, Sincerely without Dissimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, speedily without Delay, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly without Fainting, that we may not all fail in our duty herein, be pleased daily more and more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal thy Heavenly Will to us, that so our Wills on Earth may answer to thy Will in Heaven, and keep us always carefull and circumspect in sincerity of Heart, to keep close
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:109636:61"/>unto it, that neither the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our own Hearts, the Seduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Satan, or the deceits or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse of this present World may at any time withdraw us from the Obedience of thy most perfect and holy Will, for Christ his sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for Christian Prudence and Circumspection, in order to a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Resistance of Temptations.</head>
               <p>MIghty and Mercifull God, I am a weak and frail Creature, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be overcome with every Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to depart from my duty to thee, and do hourly converse with all va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Temptations from the World, from the Prince of it, and what is worst of all, from my own sinful heart, corrupt Nature and unruly Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and without thy continual Grace preventing or assisting me the least
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:109636:62"/>of all these Temptations are able to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermatch me, and because I am ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to Temptations in all my A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Conditions, Wants, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments; And since all our ways are before thee, and thou kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>west the snares that be in them, how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them or, to prevent us from them, or to preserve us against them, I beseech thee, by thy Providence pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve me from all those Temptations which thou knowest to be too strong for me, and by thy Grace, preserve me from being overcome by those Temptations that unavoidably occur in all our Actions and Conditions. Grant me the spirit of Watchfulness and Sobriety, the Spirit of Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Humility, the Spirit of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Circumspection, the Spirit of Patience and Wisdom, the Spirit of Faith and Dependance, the Spirit of the Love and Fear of thy Majesty, that may support me against all those Temptations to any sin that may meet me in the course and passage of my Life, that tho' thy Providence
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:109636:62"/>should permit me to fall into Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, I may not fall under it, but by thy Grace be delivered from the Evil of it, through the merits and Spirit of the most Admirable Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Resolute stedfastness to our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tismal Covenant.</head>
               <p>BLessed and Holy Saviour: Give me Grace to remember my Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tismal Vow, to remember that I am a sworn Enemy to the World, the Flesh, and the Devil, and enable me to fight the good fight of Faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that banner of thine, the Cross. Let me have no Truce, Entertain no friendship with thine and my Enemies: Let them flatter me, if they will, with smiles and promises, I am sure they mean nothing to me but Death and Ruin. How shall any fantastical obligations
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:109636:63"/>cancel my duty to thee, resulting from so solemn a covenant. In vain does the World disguise its Temptation under the form of Civility and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; I know no Civility which would betray me to dispense with my Vows, no Honour that can excuse Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury. In vain does the World assault me by Earthly Greatness, Wealth, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. These are the very things I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd against when I took up the Cross of my Crucify'd Saviour in Baptism. Grant, O Blessed Lord, that I may have mortifi'd Affections and a victorious Faith, an Humble Meek spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Glorious Hopes, that after this troublesome Life is ended I may rest with thee in everlasting Glory.</p>
               <trailer>Amen, Amen.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:109636:63"/>
               <head>For Trust in God.</head>
               <p>O Almighty Lord, who never fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est them that trust on thee, give me Grace, I beseech thee, in all my disficulties and distresses to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to thee to rest and depend on thee. Thou shalt keep him, O Lord, in perfect Peace whose mind is staid on thee. O let me alway rest on this firm Pillar, and never Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change it for the broken Reeds of Worldly Succours. Suffer not my heart to be overcharged with the cares of this Life, taking thought what I shall eat or drink or wherewithall I shall be cloathed; but grant that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by honest Labour and Industry carefully done my part, chearfully commit my self to thy Providence casting all my care upon thee, who carest for me, and being carefull for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to be of the number of those
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:109636:64"/>whom thou ownest, and carest for, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven such as keep thy Testimonies and think upon thy Commandments to do them, that seeking first thy Kingdom and the Righteousness there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, all these outward things may be added unto me in such a measure as thy Wisdom knows best for me: Grant this, O Lord, for Jesus Christ his sake.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the Cure of backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to the Holy Communion.</head>
               <p>O My God, what should make me so prodigally venturous as to neglect the frequent use of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament of the Lords Supper. Have I not need frequently to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine my self? Are not the Graces thou givest me apt to wither and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay unless thus water'd and refresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Does not my converse with the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:109636:64"/>World and my Communication with Flesh and Blood, render it necessary for me to renew my Resolutions against them as often as I can? Or is there not a holy delight in the Exercise of all this, that surpas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses all the pleasures of a sensual life? And is it not a sacrifice that my Lord and Saviour is highly pleased with? And is it not reasonable that I should oblige him who died for me, with this frequent acknowledgment of his infinite Love evidenc'd in his Death? Pardon me, O my God, that I have been so ungratefull to thee, and so senseless of my own Welfare and Advantage: Henceforward I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve to frequent and delight in this Holy Communion; I will often of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up my self a Sacrifice to thee and profess my Faith in a Crucified Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and there beg thy Assistance and Conduct of my endanger'd Soul, thro' the difficult paths of this present life. O my God, prosper and accept these my Addresses, Resolutions, and Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, through thine infinite Mercies,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:109636:65"/>and the Inestimable Blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Divine fervour of Spirit.</head>
               <p>O Glorious God, 'tis the sole ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence of my Nature that I am capable of loving thee, and it is my Glorious Privilege that thou art plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to suffer and admit of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses of my Soul. In this only I am a Kin to Angels. In those Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents which serve only to the end of a Corporal Life, I am out-done by Brutes: O give me therefore grace to dwell as often as I can in the Divine Contemplations of thy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; to look forward to that glory which thy Bounty hath reveal'd and promis'd me; to consider by what Methods thou didst prepare me for it; and let all this make me love thee above all things, and desire to know nothing but thee my Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:109636:65"/>Father, and Jesus Christ and him Crucifi'd.</p>
               <trailer>Amen, Amen.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Affiance in God's Spirit.</head>
               <p>O My God how reasonable is it that I should obey thee since thou Commandest me nothing but what thou givest strength to perform. I feel the weakness of my Nature and the strength of my Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But this shall never discourage me, through the Might of thy spirit I shall be sure to Conquer: It must be a weakness indeed which Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence cannot relieve; It must be a strange assault made by the World which can storm that Fort which the spirit of the Almighty defends, and that Love must be more than Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed above the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of a Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> inspired and actua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thee. No, no, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thou vouchsafest
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:109636:66"/>but one Ray of thine infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Power I shall soon subdue the World and Mortifie the Spirit: I shall do the things which please thee here, and shall obtain Everlasting Life afterwards, which grant for thy Mercies sake, and thy Son Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus sake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Perseverance.</head>
               <p>O Eternal and Unchangeable Lord God, who art the same yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, to day and for ever. Be thou plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to communicate some small Ray of that Excellence to the degree of that stability to me thy wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Creature, who am light and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constant, turn'd about with every blast. My Understanding is very deceivable. O establish it in thy Truth, keep it from the snares of seducing Spirits, that I may not be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> led away with the error of the wicked, and fall from
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:109636:66"/>my own stedfastness. My Will also, O Lord, is irresolute and wavering, and doth not cleave stedfastly unto God. My goodness is but as the morning Cloud, and as the early dew it passeth away. O strengthen and confirm me, and whatever good work thou hast wrought in me, be pleased to accomplish and perform it till the day of Christ. Lord, thou seest my weakness, and thou knowest the number and strength of those Temptations I have to struggle with: O leave me not to my self, but co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou my Head in the day of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and in all spiritual Combates, Make me more than Conqueror, thro' him that loved me. O let no Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors or Flatteries either of the World or my own Flesh ever draw me from my obedience to thee; but grant that I may continue stedfast, immoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, and by patient continuing in well-doing; seek, and at last obtain Glory, and Honour, and Immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Eternal life, thro' Jesus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:109636:67"/>
               <head>For an awakning sense of our Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</head>
               <p>O Holy Jesus, thou Lord of Life and Glory, who by thy death hast overcome Death, and open'd the Gate of everlasting Life, at the hour of Death and the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, good Lord deliver me. Grant that I may so think of my latter end that the end of my life on Earth may be the beginning to me of a Blessed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity in Heaven; that the second Death, the never ceasing one, may have no dominion over me; but that when I discontinue living with Men I may dwell with thee our God, and converse with all the Blessed Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty above. Grant, Heavenly Father, that when I come to lie on a Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, I may be able to look backward with Comfort and Consolation on a
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:109636:67"/>well spent Life, and forward with a bright Prospect of Glory and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality beyond the Grave, that when I am nigh unto Death, and my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily strength languisheth, my Faith and Hope may revive and become vigorous, and I may then feel the Joyous approaches of that Salvation which I before had wrought out with fear and trembling. I know, O lord, that 'tis appointed to all Men once to die, and that no one can rescue his Life from the Pit of Destruction, and yet do we live as if we had made an agreement with Hell, and had an unforfeitable lease of our Lives. O give me to die unto sin now that I may sleep in Christ at my departure, and be awaken'd, be raised to Life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at the Restitution of all things. Afford me some of the refreshing beams of thy Reconciled Countenance when passing through the dark Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of the shadow of death. Grant that I may then fear no evil, but have the Testimony of a good Conscience, which may be a supporting Cordial to
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:109636:68"/>my weak and fainting spirits. Grant that I may not live in such an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared state of Soul as that I should be afraid to die and appear before thy Judgment feat, but cause me so to demean my self as that the sting and terror of Death, Sin, may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away before Death it self lays hold on me, that when it comes I may welcome it with smiles and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and may lift up my head with Joy at my hasting Dissolution, as knowing that then the Time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draweth nigh. Be thou present with me at the hour of death. O blessed Jesus who sufferedst death for us upon the Cross? By the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that thy precious Death, sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, I beseech thee, the bitterness of ours; when our eyes shall be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en'd in the Agonies of Death, kindle in my heart the light of saying Faith; when speech shall fail and leave me, O do thou speak inwardly unto me by the comforts of thy spirit, and grant that I may speak mentally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee by devout sights and groans
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:109636:68"/>which cannot be uttered; when I am nigh to the end of my days, may I be nigh to the end of my hope e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Salvation of my Soul. O give me in my last extremity Joy in believing, hope in my latter end, humble Resignation of my spirit into thy Hands, and Holy contempt of this Earth, and Inflamed Love of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, longing desires to be with our Saviour Christ with Angels and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifi'd Saints which is much better than being here. <hi>Amen,</hi> for thy Mercies sake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:109636:69"/>
               <head>For a Practical Remembrance of the day of Judgment.</head>
               <p>O Blessed Saviour, thou most. Righteous Judge Eternal, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd by thy Father to be Judge both of the Quick and Dead, whereof he hath given us assurance in that he hath raised thee from the Dead. O raise me from the Death of Sin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Life of Righteousnes, and hereby fit and prepare me for the day of Judgment. Cause me so ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to think on it at present, as that I may not dread its terrors here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, but may be justifi'd by thy sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and clear'd when I am Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not trusting in my own Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, which is but as filthy Rags, but being Cloath'd with the imputed Righteousness which is of God, thro' Faith in Christ Jesus. O that when
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:109636:69"/>I am Judged I may be found in him, having an Interest in the Merits of his Death and Passion; that he who is to be our Judge, may likewise be our Advocate and Acquitter! Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed be God the Father, Blessed be the Holy Trinity, that thou Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Jesus art to be our Judge, who by assuming Humane Nature wast touch'd with a fellow-feeling of our Infirmities being in all points tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as we are yet without sin, that thou mightest have Compassion on us thy Brethren who are tempted; and that we might come the more boldly to thy Judgment seat, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace to help in that greatest time of need. O may we obtain Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, when our Lord enters into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with us! may we be acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted when try'd! May our Saviour look on all he had done, on all he has suffered in Man's behalf, when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Inquisition what we have done, spoke, or thought, and may he for the satisfaction purchased by his Blood be gracious unto us. Give us, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:109636:70"/>God so to accuse and condemn our selves for sin by a Penitent ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of it, that we may not be condemned in thy fearfull Judgment, but may stand in the Judgment as found upright and absolved therein. O that my own heart may pass that true Judgment on me in this World, which thou, Blessed Redeemer, wilt pass on me in the other, and if up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on calling my self to an Account, at present I find that my Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence condemns me. Grant that I may make void that Condemnation by immediate Amendment, considering that if my heart condemn me, thou, our God, art greater than our hearts, and knowing all things wilt much more condemn me. Allay, Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, by the pleadings of thy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation and Intercession, the Rigour and Severity of thy Final Sentence. Cause me to live as if I ever heard that roaring Sentence in my Ears, <hi>Awake ye Dead, and come to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> O make me in Apprehension hereof to Judge and Examine my
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:109636:70"/>past courses and to correct and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form whatever I find amiss in them, that the Habitual Remembrance of the last day of Tryal may quicken me unto a more than ordinary Holy Preparation for it, that I may expect it with a Comfortable Hope, meet it with an humble well-grounded As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance, be acquitted in it, plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Lord's most perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and relying wholly on his most Meritorious Expiration, and may I at length be blessed with the ravish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Approbation, <hi>Come thou Blessed Child Inherit the Kingdom prepared for thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:109636:71"/>
               <head>For a Practical Belief and Prospect of the Joy of Heavens.</head>
               <p>O Sovereign Excellency and most exalted Blessedness, whose de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightsome presence makes Heaven. O grant that having such an exceeding and Eternal heighth of Glory for the object of my Faith and Hope, I may labour after an Heavenly Frame and Disposition in my Soul, which may qualifie me for the Celestial state hereafter: Grant that I having given unto me such precious promises as those in the Gospel appertaining to this Life, and a better, may be the incitement of these become a parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of thy Divine Nature, escaping the Corruptions which are in the World through Lust: O holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, give me a lively view of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by an Eye of Faith, and so raise
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:109636:71"/>up my mind thither, that I may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways have my Thoughts, my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, my Conversation there, whence I look for the Saviour, O make me such an obedient Subject of thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Grace, that I may be made capable of thy Kingdom of Glory. Enable me, Heavenly Father more to admire those inexhaustible Treasures of thy goodness, prepared for such as Love and Fear thee, which Eye hath not seen, nor Ear heard, which have not entred into the heart of Man to conceive. O thy unmeasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable goodness whereby we are not only delivered from suffering the Vengeance of Hell Torments, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so made capable of the Enjoyments of Heaven. What shall I render un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord for all these Inestima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble benefit which he designs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow upon us? O give me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form my self to thine Image in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, that I may behold thee, our God in Glory, where certainly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be wanting, where all wise Desires and Expectations will
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:109636:72"/>be compleatly gratifi'd, because thou our supreme happiness wilt be All in All to us. O let me be thine and be thou mine to all Eternity. <hi>Amen,</hi> and <hi>Amen,</hi> Blessed Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For a Sanctifi'd Fear of Hell,</head>
               <p>O Most Just and Impartially Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Divine Being, who so ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that thou punishedst it in thine own Son, that thou pursuest it with Eternal Vengeance in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World; O grant that by thy Threatning of Hell Torments I may be preserv'd from ever coming there, and be deterr'd from those wicked Actions which lead directly thither: May I answer the end of thy creating an Hell by improving the dread there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of into that obediential Love which bringeth to Heaven. Make me sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:109636:72"/>Blessed Lord, of thy equal mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and loving kindness in preparing a Tophet a place of Punishment, as in providing a Heaven a place of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Recompence for the persever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly Good and Righteous, in that thou didst intend by those different objects of our Hopes and Fears, to address thy self differently to our va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Tempers and Dispositions, and to drive those to their duty and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness by thy Denunciations of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, who would not be led to their duty and happiness, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of future Glory and Felicity. O how graciously hast thou hedged in our way to Everlasting Bliss on every side! using all means that we should not err and depart from it! What couldst thou have done for us which thou hast not done? We have an Heaven to allure to obedience, we have an Hell to deterr from every wilfull Impiety: How utterly inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sable must I needs be then if I break through all these Fences and Sanctions of thy Laws? Put, gracious God, thy
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:109636:73"/>fear into my inner parts, and make me tremble at thy Judgments; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aw'd by them into an holy cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I at no time willfully of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee. O grant that I knowing the terrors of thee, O Lord, may effectually be perswaded to a break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off my Sins, and an applying my self to holiness. Give me Grace to escape as for my Life out of the sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Sodom of every wicked Impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, never so much as looking back upon them with an Eye of Compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, lest the flames due to them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertake me unawares. Cause me, I beseech thee, to flee from Sin by the awakening Consideration of its being the only way whereby to flee from the wrath to come: O may the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of Hell punishments restrain both my Inclinations and my Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from both the pleasures and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of sin, which are but for a season. Give me often, Holy Father, to ask my self these startling, deterring que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions, when about to sin wilfully; How can I do this great Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:109636:73"/>and by sinning against God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke his infinite Justice and Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty power to punish me? Who of us can dwell with everlasting burnings? Is it not a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the ever living God, who is a consuming fire? Is it not a most horrid Misery to be Eternally seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Death, and yet never to find it in the Regions of darkness and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spair? O cause me to dread and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor sin, which leads to this place of Eternal Torments as much as the suffering place it self. Cause me to think often on Hell, that I may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be kept from falling into it: Grant, O Holy Jesu, thou who art the Resurrection and the Life, that I may never fall into the bitter pains of Eternal Death; what else can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose me as fuel to Hell flames but my sins? They are the Combustible Matter which the fire which cannot be quench'd will ever be preying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Give me therefore, good Lord, to burn up that Immoral Hay, and Straw, and Stubble at present, and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:109636:74"/>then the fire prepar'd for the Devil and his Angels, will have no power over me, neither will so much as the smell thereof have past upon me; but I shall be received into Everlasting ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations of Heavenly Glory and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Generous Compassion to One's Country, and a hearty readiness to promote the Reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</head>
               <p>O Most Holy Lord God, who art terrible in thy Judgments to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Children of Disobedience, who for the sins of mankind didst once drown the whole World, eight Souls excepted, and didst also rain Fire and Brimstone upon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> for the sinfullness of them that dwelt therein; I acknowledge and confess in behalf of my self and all
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:109636:74"/>the People of this Kingdom that we have justly deserv'd thy severest Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for we have all gone astray and dealt wickedly, we have openly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd and ridicul'd Vertue and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and have set up and encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all manner of Vice and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness, we have dishonoured thy Name, defil'd thy House, profan'd thy Worship, and slighted thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Nay, O Lord, we have been so hardy that we have been insensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble under thy Punishments, and that which thou in Mercy didst design to reform and amend us, has serv'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make us more Obstinate and Rebellious against thee. We have made our selves slaves to the World, the Flesh and the Devil, and have engag'd our selves in a War against Heaven; and have fought against our own Happiness. And now, O God, what can we expect from thee but Judgment and fiery Indignation, which is indeed the due reward of our sins? We must confess that we are ripe for Destruction, and ought every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:109636:75"/>to expect to have the World set on Fire about us. But, O Lord, thou art a Mercifull God, to thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long Mercies and Forgivenesses tho' we have rebell'd against thee and have not obey'd thy Voice by walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in those Laws which thou hast set before us. Deal not with us therefore, O merciful Lord, after our sins, neither reward us after our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, but let thy Anger, and thy Wrath be turn'd away from us, and bring us not into Confusion. Let the Prayers and Tears of those few Pious Souls who mourn in secret for the sins of this abominable People, stop thy avenging Hand, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with thee to allow us a little more time for Repentance. Bring us to a sense of our fins and a dread of thy Judgments, that so we may not dare to provoke thee any more, but may humble our selves before thee, in a most Sincere and Sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Contrition of heart, that thou being pleased therewith, may'st repent thee of the evil which thou hast said
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:109636:75"/>thou wouldst do it to us, and do it not. O that as our Corruption and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generacy has been National so our Repentance, Humiliation, and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation may be National too? O prosper the endeavours which some noble Souls amongst us have us'd to pluck us out of our wretched Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Pardon and alter the minds of all who openly oppose and abuse, of all who secretly undermine, of all who are not, convinced of the necessity of their endeavours. Pardon, and alter all who are Hypocritical Friends to their Cause: Give me and all of all Ranks mongst us an Unfeigned and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous regard for our Country and the promotion of thy Glory and true Christianity amongst us. Grant that the Magistrates and Ministers with a sincere and noble spirit may do their parts: Let not Cowardice or selfish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness with-hold us from honestly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming against bold offenders: O suffer us not for shame or interest to be Traytors to God, to the Laws, and our Prince, who have espous'd
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:109636:76"/>their own cause, and grant that the Known and Habitual and Exemplary Candour, Courtesie, Prudence, Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Diligence in their Calling, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty, Mercy, Meekness, and all other Christian Vertues, may recommend all engag'd in it and free them and their endeavours to reform us, from being rashly ensur'd, as serving private Interests by it. Lord, give us a truly Divine Zeal against thy Enemies and for the wellfare of this Country, and having put such a Spirit into us, ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us, if the head strong Wickedness of a foolish and unreclaim'd people should require it, to' lay down our Lives rather than not bravely oppose the Devils interest; make us meek in our behaviours, to those who unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably revile us. Be our Guard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst those who through their Zeal to uphold those Lewd shews and places which are the Nurseries of Lewdness and Idleness, and have turn'd <hi>London</hi> into a <hi>Sodom,</hi> lay in wait for your Lives: Lord hear, Lord forgive, hearken and change
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:109636:76"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r disappoint their designs: Turn their Malice into thoughts of Cane for their Everlasting wellfare and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>arposes of Love instead of their <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ormer Enmity against Souls, Christ <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd their Country. Hear for thine <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>finite Compassions sake. <hi>Amen.</hi> O Grant that by a Communication of <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e Diffusive spirit of Jesus, we may no <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nger every one seek only his own <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ings, and serve mean Interests, but <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l act as those that remember we <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ere made not for a separate feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but for the Enjoyment of an <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>finite God, and a vast World of Glorifi'd Beings. This also I beg <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r the sake of Jesus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:109636:77"/>
               <head>For Discretion in the choice of a Friend.</head>
               <p>TEach me, good God, to know the weakness of my frame, and the Treachery and Uncertainty of all that is therein; and since, Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing my good will may be Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal, I can be usefull to but a few, point out and procure to me such persons as thou knowest may both benefit and be benefitted most by me for the objects of my Friendship and Familiarity, that my choice depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on thy direction and being dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by thy will I may never have just cause to repent of my Contracts, but my Companions being pious and serviceable to the most extensive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests of my Soul, I may daily find fresh cause of lauding thee on their behalf, who honour and benefit me by
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:109636:77"/>a generous and Christian Intimacy. <hi>Amen,</hi> for Christ his sake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Faithfullness and Gratitude to a Friend.</head>
               <p>INstruct, Incite, and Enable me, O Lord, I beseech thee frequently to manifest the Sincerity and Vigor of my Love to all those who have been Ministers of good to me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy gracious Providence. O ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver suffer me to provoke my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science to upbraid me of Unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Treachery, and Ingratitude to any to whom I have betroath'd my Soul in the bond of Friendship and from whom I have received many Pledges of Sincere and Honourable Love. Treasure up their Favours se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely in my Memory and give me power to Make suitable returns to them. And because all other use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullness
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:109636:78"/>will not suffice to make them happy unless they be vertuous and use all their Opportunities and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperities to thy Glory: Make me heartily to abhor all Flattery, Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simulation, and Hypocritical Love and Delight, which may encline me to connive at any thing that is sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in my Friend. Give me cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to frown in due season, and when my contract cannot but be vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated unless, Beauteous God, my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for my Friend be regulated by the Love of thy Commands, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me not, O Lord, to turn my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kindnesses into Curses, by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding any seasonable Admonitions, Counsels, and Repro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fs, lest other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise we prove eternal Enemies and Eternally odious to thee, our selves, and each other, in an Everlasting Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment from Love and Light, even the Light of thy Countenance, from which, good Lord, deliver me, for the Love and Mercies of Jesus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:109636:78"/>
               <head>For Gentleness.</head>
               <p>GOD of wonderfull Long-suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Gentleness, give me a powerfull sense of thy amazing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descention, and the Exemplary Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>leness which thy Son shew'd to the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>firmities of men, when he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>f'd to wear our Nature and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rse with frail mortal Creatures: Grant that I may remember my own reakness, and shew all Candour to all <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>en. Let me be readier to relieve and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>elp any Neighbours weakness rather than censure and expose him. Make <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e easie of Access and easie in Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ation, and alway ready rather to yield to others in matters of any in different Nature, than by adoring my own humour contentiously, and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my own Judgment Conceitedly, and Idolatrously to unhinge my own,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:109636:79"/>and the minds of others. Hear this request in the Name of the Son of thy Love. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Patience and Resignation.</head>
               <p>O Father of Mercies and God of all Comforts, who to all thy other Benefits wherewith thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually loadest us, hast bestow'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us the Gospel of thy Grace, that we through Patience and Comfort of the holy Scriptures might have hope. Accept of the humble and thankfull acknowledgments which I make to thy Divine Goodness, for thy riches of Mercy in Christ Jesus, who was pleas'd for our sakes to humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to Death, even the Death of the Cross, and with great Patience to suffer the sharpest Pains and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonies with many Reproaches and Contradictions of sinners: And when
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:109636:79"/>he was oppressed, afflicted, and Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phem'd, yet silently endur'd, being brought as a Lamb to the Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and as a Sheep before the Shearer is dumb, so open'd he not his mouth. I praise and magnifie with all my Soul his wonderfull Love to us, and his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Subjection to thee, beseeching thee to give me such a gratefull sense of his ineffable Love, such an ardent Love to his Memory, and such an high ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of his glorious Example that I may be inspir'd thereby, with Christian Resolution to follow after him in all the Paths of Humble, Meek, and Patient Vertue. O that I may feel my self press'd by the mighty power of that Love, not only to be a doer of thy Will, but for Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence toward thee, my God, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure grief, suffering wrongfully, and to run with Patience the whole Race that is set before me, looking unto Jesus, the Author and Finishev of our Faith; who, for the Joy that was set before him, endured the Cross, despising the shame, and is set down
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:109636:80"/>at the Right hand of the Throne of God. Preserve in me such a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence towards thee, Father of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that I may neither despise nor faint under thy Corrections: But tho' thou bringest me into great and sore troubles, I may still be in Subjection unto thee, and live in hope of that Immortal Glory. And not only so, but I may rejoyce and glory also in Tribulation, for Christ's sake, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Tribulation worketh Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Patience Experience, and Experience Hope, and Hope maketh not asham'd. And whatsoever the Cross be, which lies in my way to Heaven: Grant that I may never turn aside from thee in the least to avoid it, but take it up willingly, and bear it as long as thou pleasest, without murmuring or repining, and with some Courage and Chearfullness of Spirit. And as for the common miseries of this Life, endue my Spirit with such principles of Wisdom, and help me to preserve it in such Innocence, Clearness, and Integrity, that it may
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:109636:80"/>be able to sustain my Infirmity; and whatsoever Sicknesses or Pains, or other bodily Calamities befal me, I may receive them, and bear them with an even and constant Mind? Knowing that as we receive good from thy hand, we ought in Reason to receive evil, and in every thing to give thanks, which is thy Will concerning us in Christ Jesus. O Blessed Lord, lead me whither thou pleasest, I will follow thee without Complaint. I submit to thy Orders, I reverence thy Wisdom, I trust my self with thy Goodness, I depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy Almighty power, I rely on thy promises, beseeching thee to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me, till Patience having its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect working in me, I may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and entire, wanting nothing. I know the time is but short, and that thou hast prepar'd long Joys to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence our Momentary sorrows: Help me therefore always to possess r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Soul in Patience at present giving thanks for the hope we have, as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor of the Soul both sure and sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fast,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:109636:81"/>fast, that so I may at last after I have done thy Will, O God, inherit the promise. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Contempt of the World.</head>
               <p>O Most amiable Divine Majesty, give me a lively Transporting Prospect of the Glories of Heaven, give me a Prospect of the Heavenly Beauties and Perfections of thine own Nature, and then how will all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary Pomps and Vanities appear dim and faded in my sight? How shall I look down with seorn and contempt upon them? Shall I still lie groveling on Earth, whilst thou allowest me to raise my thoughts to thee, and to exalt them above this World? Wilt thou admit and accept our weak imperfect Affections, and shall not I do all I can to elev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te and spiritualize them for thy service? O give me that Victory of Faith where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:109636:81"/>by I may overcome the World, that assurance of Hope, whereby I may live above its Corruptions, Purifying my self even as thou art Pure. Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie in me, O Sovereign Excellency, the Love of the World with the quickening inflam'd Love of thy self; shew thy self a loving Father and it sufficeth: A glance of the Light of thy Countenance, is enough to Eclipse all Earthly splendour. O make me to see the Vanity of all things here below, and then I shall soon discern the vanity of my Affections in inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately doting on them. Cause me, O Spirit of Divine Grace to consider how the Lord of Life and Glory despis'd and contemn'd the World. Make me to evidence my daily contempt of this World, by the coldness and indifferency of my love towards it, by wanting its Enjoyments without Impatience, by possessing them with Temperance and Moderation, and by losing them without murmuring and discontent. Perswade me, O Lord, effectually perswade me, that
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:109636:82"/>I can never be Happy till I have dis-entangled my Affections from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Empty, Unsatisfying, Disappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Transient good here below, and till I love thee above all things who alone canst fill-our Desires and gratifie all our Wishes; till I despise this World, think lowly of my self, highly of my God, and am wholly Dead and Crucifi'd to all my sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sual Lusts and Appetites. O come thou then unto me, O our God, come and satisfie my Soul with thy full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. Replenish it with thy likeness and holiness, and thereby drive out of me all Inordinate Love for mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Objects and Gratifications. <hi>Amen,</hi> Blessed Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:109636:82"/>
               <head>For a wise Zeal.</head>
               <p>BLessed and Glorious Lord God, who infinitely deservest our most Warm and Zealous Services, who makest thy Angels Spirits, and those, thy Ministers, a flame of fire; flames indeed of Devotion, of Divine Love and Gratitude, of Delight and Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in holy Obedience. O make me also all flame and spirit in thy Worship and Service: Make me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways mindfull that Religion and the Salvation of my Soul, is the one thing needfull, a matter of the vast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Importance. Make me therefore, I beseech thee, to serve thee as one that beateth not the Air: Give me to covet earnestly the best gifts, to seek the Lord and his Strength, and his Righteousness, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, since they are the most Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things, with my whole Soul and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:109636:83"/>Might. Give, give me, good Lord, more Love to thee, our God, that I may have a greater Zeal for thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory, boldly rebuke Vice, and with the Desire of Desire pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Holiness. May my heart burn within me for Joy, when thy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Prayer, or Tranksgiving are my Employment. Let my heart be sad when I see others Sin boldly, or find my Affections cold and languid in thy Service: O may I count it my meat and drink to be doing thy Will. O Pardon the Heartlesness of my best performances, and cure the Earthliness of my Affections. Make me alway zealously Affected in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good matter, and my zeal to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and his Service, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Knowledge, <hi>Amen.</hi> By his Grace and for his sake, who alway went about doing good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:109636:83"/>
               <head>For the Grace of Gratulation.</head>
               <p>INfinite Love and Beauty, who hast commanded us by thy Holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to rejoyce with all that rejoyce; Enrobe my Soul, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee with that Angelick tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Charity, which will force me to rejoyce in all the solid Joy and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of all Beings: O that I may so triumphantly rejoyce in all the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent Perfections of thee, my God, both Communicable and Incommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as to long to be dissolv'd and to see thee in Heaven where thou art Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped and Adored by all thy elect Angels and Saints! O that I had a heart so strongly sensible of thy Glory, as to be able with Good grounds to say, <hi>I would love and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thee with all that Love and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, where with all thy Angels and Saints
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:109636:84"/>do there love and serve thee, if it were in my power.</hi> 'Tis my desire to Joy in all the Loves and Services, that the Just men of the Church in all former Ages in the present or in the future Ages, have, and do, or shall hear and perform towards thee, and I do rejoyce in the prospect of a time, when all Nations shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Nations of God and the Kingdoms of his Christ, Kingdoms of Righteousness and Peace and Love. Hasten, hasten the time, O dear spouse, of Souls: O that my Love and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire towards thee, O my God, were such and so great that if it were possible to me, and acceptable to thee, I would of each Soul and especially my own make a Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that thou mightest be prais'd and beloved in as many Heavens as there are Souls by Infinite Myriads of large Souls more in number, than the Grass-piles of the Sea shouting forth thy Praises, and Blessed with a noble Conformity of Being to the Uncrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:109636:84"/>Harmony, Holiness, and Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness by the Beatifick Vision of and Union to thy boundless fullness and Majesty. O may my Soul entirely be sanctifi'd, Gratulate that infinite and self-originated Wisdom, Royalty, Goodness, Simplicity, Incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibleness, Power, Justice, and Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability which thou hast been, and wilt be, invested with from and to all Eternity. Gratulated be our God with all the Constancy, Acceptable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and Ability, the grace of Christ can give me, that he is a Being of such Immense Facundity, as to be a fully sufficient treasure of ever-sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying Enjoyment, both for himself and all his Creatures, that he is so rich and happy a Nature that the whole Creation and all its Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, can add nothing to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, which he already has and did ever possess. I desire likewise, O Lord, to rejoyce with an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguish'd Fervour, Thankfullness and Psalmody of Soul, together with thee, and the Glorious Inhabitants of the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:109636:85"/>Triumphant Universe in the sweet Ordinance and Disposition of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, and for all the things which are in the marvellous Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this World, and for all the things which thou hast made, and shalt yet make unto the end of the World, and the Consummation of all things. I Congratulate and rejoyce with thee, O my God, in all the land and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, which the Angels and Saints in Heaven and thy Servants on Earth do give thee, and for all the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship they yield unto thee. Because I find my self altogether insufficient to praise my God, I do for my help and assistance therein invite and call upon the holy Angels and all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and with them I joyn my own Soul with all the Powers of it, that all of them together may glorifie God for his infinite Excellency. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce further in the Dignity of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, in the Rewards of all that he did, suffered and accepted as a Man for Man, I gratulate the Mystical U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Uncreated Word to our
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:109636:85"/>frail Nature, his Triumphs over Hell, Death, Sin, and the Devil, and his Conquests of Apostacy, Mights, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, Thrones, and Principalities and Confederate spiritual Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in high places; by his Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Ascension, Mission of the Holy Ghost on the day of Pentecost and Exaltation, as Mediatour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Man at the Right hand of the Father in the highest Heavens; whence, as a Royal Prince and Saviour: He pour'd down a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of Helps, Healings, Governments, and Prophesies, and still by his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercession, and Spirit conveys Grace, Peace, Mercy, and Truth, and Hope, and Comfort, and all Holiness to his Elect, who address, and serve, and rely on him, and long by the Compleat, Sanctificatory and Perfect Love to be one with Christ as he is one with thee, O our God.</p>
               <p>O Life of my Soul, O thou only source of Blessedness and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, my heart is ready, O God, my heart is ready. Lord, what is
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:109636:86"/>there in Heaven or what upon Earth that I would have besides thee? Why is my sojourning prolong'd? when shall I be there where Love and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation, and Praise will be my whole Exercise? As the Hart thirsteth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Waters, so should my Soul thirst after that State, O God; why desire I not to be dissolv'd and to be with Christ? O that I may be so conform'd to the Earthly, and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifi'd as to bear the Image of the Heavenly and Glorifi'd Jesus! Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed are they who dwell in thy House, they will be always praising thee: O Life of my Soul, and the pleasant repose of my Spirit: Wound me, Wound the most inward parts of my Soul, with the darts of thy Love: when shall all die in me, which is contrary to thee? When shall I live to be no more mine own? When shall nothing else live in me but thou, O Jesus? When shall the flames of thy Love wholly consume me? When shall I be altogether melted and pierc'd through with the wonderfull
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:109636:86"/>Efficacy of thy sweetness? When wilt thou free me from all these Clogs and Distractions, and make me one Spirit with thee, that I may not any more depart from thee? O dearly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of my Soul? O sweetness of my Heart? O God of my Soul? Why givest not thou thy self to thy poor Creature? Thou fillest Heaven and Earth, and wilt thou leave my Heart empty? Too late have I known thee, O Infinite Goodness. Woe to the time I lov'd thee not! Blind I was that I saw thee not! Thou wast within me, and I went seeking thee abroad! But now that I have found thee, though late, suffer not, good Lord that I ever leave thee. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:109636:87"/>
               <head>For Revernce to Inspiration in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry.</head>
               <p>O Father of all Light and Truth, who of thy Wisdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, hast made me a Creature of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and capable of improving my Ideal Capacity, by enquiry in a state of tryal, which if diligently and humbly Regulated by the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thy Word, will be reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and replenish'd with the Visions of Heaven: Lauded be thy Name for this capacity, lauded be thy Name that when 'twas deprav'd by sin, and the light within us was darkness, thou didst relieve it by the Wisdom of the Patriarchs and Prophets, and Evangelists and Apostles, which they received from thy Spirit, and the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:109636:87"/>Word of thine own Son. O grant that I may have a just sense and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>estimable value of this Light, and govern my Enquiry and Belief entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Authority of it: May this be my fix'd rule to Judge by, in this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Age wherein Opinion and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie usurp all orders of Men amongst us: Lord, give us all more Modesty and regard to thy Word, that we may not believe every Spirit and every fair Schme of Science, falsly so call'd, but knowing that false Prophets and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Spirits are gone out amongst us, may soberly try the Spirits, and not think beyond or contrary to what is written in the Oracles of Christ. Make us true lovers of Peace, Sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicious of our own Judgments, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors of our false Prejudices, and Courteous to Men of all perswasions in Indifferent matters, but by no means under the pretence of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull Moderation be Flatterers of Schismaticks and contemners of the Mysteries of the Gospel, but hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Mystery of Faith and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:109636:88"/>in a pure Conscience may not wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as others, ever learning from new fangled Traditions of mens Inventions and having mens persons in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and never coming to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, but be fix'd in the practical knowledge of Christ's Doctrines here, and participate of the Uncreated Light, in a liberal measure of Glory in a future World, through Jesus Christ our Lord. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Submission and Respect to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours.</head>
               <p>GOD of order, who didst give some Prophets, some Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists, and some Teachers, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours, and hast appointed a Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Priests to the end of the World, as I beseech thee to give them Judgment and Grace to discharge their Apostolical office with Honour
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:109636:88"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o our Religion, and a faithfull and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rue Heart. So I beseech thee, teach and dispose me always to submit to those that have the Rule over us, as remembring that 'tis their place to Watch over our Souls to our everlasting good, and that they deserve double Honour, Esteem, and Love for their Works sake. Give me a heart al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to respect their persons for the sake of their Office, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to despise the youth or aggravate the weakness of the meanest of thy Ministers or to be alienated from the value of Religion, to the scandalous Lives of the worst of them, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pity and pray against their offences and the infirmities even of the faithfullest Stewards and Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers of the Mysteries of the Gospel. O may I ever esteem these rich Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures hid in Vessels of Earth, and consider the Immortality of that word of Life rather than the frailty of the speaker; alway hearing the Word of God, as the Word of God, and not as the Word of Man. Suffer me not to
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:109636:89"/>straggle from their Administrations, as too many do, to the breach of Unity and growth of Infidelity in these Libertine times: Make me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways remember that thou hast fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told that offences would come, and make me one of those steddy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of thine, whom neither scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, nor any malice or device of Devils or Men, can turn aside from the Faith; that so honouring thee in thy Ministers and Ordinances in an Age when both are so much slighted, I may be honoured by thee, Great and Holy Jesu, before Angels and Men at the Great Day. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:109636:89"/>
               <head>For Poverty in Spirit.</head>
               <p>INfinite fullness, make me, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee, sensible that nothing, no not even the imperfect Holiness of this Life can satisfie a Soul, and O may the repeated Consideration of this great Truth, further my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of another World, that my Soul being enlarged by the Noble desires of the poor in spirit may be empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all false apprehensions of things, and being stripp'd of self and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of happiness from Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things may be full of God, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitated for the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and at length arrive at unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Bliss, by the Enjoyment of Sabbaths, and Royalties, and Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, and Visions, and Charities, and Fullnesses, and Unions, and all the Eternal Joys of thy Eternal King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, so be it, all Glorious Jesu. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:109636:90"/>
               <head>For Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghost.</head>
               <p>GOD, whose Peace passeth man's Understanding and the Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients of whose Kingdom is Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, and Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghost: Plant, I beseech thee, a firm and flourishing Habit of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Righteousness in my Soul, that I may have an abstract of the Kingdom of Heaven within me, and be possess'd of that Peace and Holy Joy which is a Pearl of great price, and which 'tis not in the power of Men to plunder me of, that so I may have delightfull Communion of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science by Faith with thee here, whilst in this P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lgrim state, and be a Bliss<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the fullness of Joy and Ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sure hereafter in the last World of Happiness and Perfection, through Jesus Christ. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:109636:90"/>
               <head>For effectual Regeneration and Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</head>
               <p>GOD, who art able and willing to reduce degenerate man from a state of darkness to a state of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Light: Speak, I beseech thee, the powerfull word toward thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. Let the Baptism of the Holy Ghost pierce the retiredest recesses of my Nature, that the Almighty fire may dispell all my darkness with its light, and consume all the dross of my affections, with its great and swift motion and force. Lord wash, Lord so purifie, Lord so enlighten, Lord so renew, Lord so transform, Lord so sanctifie me, that I may be freed from the Condemnation with the World, and to my endless comfort may be found Interested in my dear and honour'd Saviour, and justified
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:109636:91"/>in the name of the Lord Jesus, and by the spirit of our God, in the Dreadfull, Universal, and Solemn Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For the Government of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</head>
               <p>JEsus, who hast said that whoever will be thy true Disciple must deny himself, and who knowest how easily we silly Creatures are betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Sense and Imagination, out of the bounds of our Christian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in our commerce with sensible objects, and from strict Judgments of the things of this World: Give me, I beseech thee, a spirit of Abstracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which may discipline my Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and keep me circumspect and wary in my Use of, and converse with Inferiour and Sublunary things. Teach me that 'tis not the Eye that
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:109636:91"/>can be satisfied with seeing or the Ear that can be satisfied with hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or the Palate with tasting? O therefore take my mind off from hankering after Feasts and Shews, and other sensual Delusions: And grant that I may eat as if I ate not, and see as if I saw not, that the frequent Contemplation of Angels and Uncreated Beauty, Musick and Banquets, may raise my heart to a scorn and abhorrence of every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate and Idolatrous Affection for Earthly and Finite objects. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> for the sake of Jesus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:109636:92"/>
               <head>For the Government of the Tongue.</head>
               <p>BLessed God, who hast Created the Body with admirable proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and conveniency of every part for the service of his intire welfare, and hast declared him a perfect man indeed who offendeth not in Word, and that if the Tongue be unbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled a man's Religion cannot be pure and undefil'd: Make me, I beseech thee, able to tame this disorderly Member, and not only to refrain from all Blasphemy, and Malicious, and Filthy Communication, but even to abominate the very hearing of it: Pardon all my past superfluity of Naughtiness by Speech, and grant that I may shew my sincere Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of it by the usefullness of my Savioury and Godly Discourse in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, henceforward always bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:109636:92"/>in mind, who has said, <hi>By thy words thou shalt be condemned, and by thy words thou shalt be justified:</hi> All which I beg, through the Merits and Mediation of Jesus Christ. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Holy and Pious Ejaculations taken out of the Book of Psalms.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O be favourable and gracious unto <hi>Sion,</hi> and build thou the Walls of <hi>Jerusalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O God, wherefore art thou absent from us so long, why is thy wrath so hot against the Sheep of thy Pasture.</p>
               <p>O think upon thy Congregation whom thou hast purchas'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd of old.</p>
               <p>Look upon the Tribe of thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance and Mount <hi>Sion</hi> wherein thou hast dwelt.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:109636:93"/>
               <p>It is time for thee, Lord, to lay to thine hand for they have destroyed thy Law.</p>
               <p>Arise, O God, and maintain thine own cause, deliver <hi>Israel,</hi> O God, out of all its troubles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Pardon of sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Call to remembrance, O Lord, thy tender mercies, which have been ever of old, O remember not the sins and offences of my youth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Light of God's Countenance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord why abhorrest thou my Soul and hidest thy Face from me! O hide not thou thy face from me, nor cast thy Servant away in displeasure.</p>
               <p>Thy Loving kindness is better than Life it self: Lord list thou up the light of thy Countenance upon me.</p>
               <p>Comfort the Soul of thy Servant, for unto thee, O Lord, do I lift up my Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King shall rejoice in thy strength O Lord, exceeding glad shall he be of thy Salvation.</p>
               <p>His honour is great in thy Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Glory and great Worship shalt
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:109636:93"/>thou lay upon him! O give him E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting Falicity, make him glad with the Joy of thy Countenance.</p>
               <p>May the King ever put his Trust in the Lord, that in the Mercy of the most high he may not mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry.</p>
               <p>Now know I that the Lord help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his anointed, and will hear him from his Holy Heaven.</p>
               <p>Be thou Exalted in thine own strength, so will we sing and praise thy power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Teach me to do the thing that pleaseth thee, for thou art my God.</p>
               <p>Teach me thy way, O Lord, and I will walk in thy truth: O knit my heart unto thee, that I may fear thy name.</p>
               <p>Make me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right spirit within me.</p>
               <p>O let my heart be sound in thy Statutes, that I be not ashamed.</p>
               <p>Incline my heart unto thy Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and not to Covetousness.</p>
               <p>Turn away mine Eyes lest they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Vanity and quicken thou me in thy way.</p>
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:109636:94"/>
               <p>I am a stranger upon Earth, O hide not thy Commandments from me.</p>
               <p>Lord, teach me to number my days that I may apply my heart unto Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When at a Christning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Reins, Lord, are thine, thou hast co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered me in my Mother's Womb. I will give thanks to thee for I am fearfully and wonderfully made.</p>
               <p>Marvellous are thy works and that my Soul knoweth right well; my Bones are not hid from thee, though I be fashioned secretly and formed beneath in the Earth.</p>
               <p>Thine Eyes did see my substance, yet being Imperfect and in thy Book, were all my members written, which day by day were fashioned when as yet there was none of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When I see Officers searching Publick hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses for prophane Persons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wilt not thou slay the Wicked, O God, they speak unrighteousness a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee, and thine Enemies take thy name in vain.</p>
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:109636:94"/>
               <p>Do not I hate them, O Lord, that hate thee, and am not I grieved with those that rise up against thee? Yea, I hate them right sore, even as tho' they were mine Enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When in dangerous Company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Set a watch, O Lord, over my mouth and keep the door of my Lips.</p>
               <p>O let not mine heart be inclined to any evil thing, let me not be occupied in Ungodly works, with the men that work Wickedness, but let me ever escape their Nets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When notice is given of a Communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will wash mine hands, O Lord, and so will I go to thine Altar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When I am provok'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Them that are meek God will guide in Judgment.</p>
               <p>Leave off from Wrath, let go Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure, fret not thy self, else shalt thou be moved to do evil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When I hear the Passing-Bell, or see a Corps.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord teach me to number my days that I may apply my Heart unto Wisdom.</p>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:109636:95"/>
               <p>Spare me, O Lord, till I am tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at peace with thee, before I go hence and am no more seen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When perplexed with doubts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord why abhorrest thou my Soul and hidest thy face from me: O hide not thou thy Face from me, nor cast away thy Servant in displeasure.</p>
               <p>Thy Loving kindness is better than Life it self.</p>
               <p>Lord, lift thou up the light of thy Countenance upon me.</p>
               <p>Comfort the Soul of thy Servant, for unto thee, O Lord, do I lift up my Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When under any scandal or disgrace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be mercifull, O Lord, be mercifull unto me, for my Soul trusteth in thee, and under the shadow of thy wings shall be my refuge untill these Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities be overpast.</p>
               <p>Deliver me, O Lord, from mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for I flee unto thee to hide me.</p>
               <p>O keep my Soul and deliver me, let me not be confounded for I have put my trust in thee, my Eyes are ever looking unto the Lord, for he shall pluck my feet out of the Net.</p>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:109636:95"/>
               <p>Turn thee, O Lord, and have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon me, for I am desolate and in misery.</p>
               <p>The sorrows of my heart are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, O bring thou me out of my troubles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When sensible of a late mercy received.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will always give thanks unto the Lord, his praise shall ever be in my mouth.</p>
               <p>Thou art my God, and I will thank thee, thou art my God and I will praise thee.</p>
               <p>I will sing unto the Lord as long as I live, I will praise my God whilst I have my being.</p>
               <p>Praised be God, which hath not cast out my prayer, nor turned his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from me.</p>
               <p>Blessed be the Lord God, even the God of <hi>Israel,</hi> which only doth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous things.</p>
               <p>How dear are thy Counsels unto me, O God: O how great is the sum of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At going out or coming in.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord bless my going out and my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, from this time forth for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:109636:96"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>At Meals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord, grant that whether I eat or drink, or whatever I do, I may do all to thy Glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At Work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prosper thou the Work of my Hands: O Lord, prosper thou my Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Shop, or at Market.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord, give me Grace to use this World so as not to abuse it.</p>
               <p>Lord, grant that I may never go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond, or defraud my Brother in any matter; for thou art the avenger of all such.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Thanksgiving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Praise the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me praise his holy name.</p>
               <p>Praise the Lord, O my Soul, while I live will I praise the Lord, yea, as long as I have any Being, will I sing praises unto my God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="181" facs="tcp:109636:96"/>
            <head>Extraordinary Devotions.</head>
            <p>ON Sundays or any other days set apart for the more solemn service of God, I chiefly observe the course of my Ordinary Devotions.</p>
            <p>On such days I always read the Collect, Epistle, and Gospel, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the day at home; as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per preparatory Duty for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick service of the Church;</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Immediately before I go to Church, I say the following Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Lord, the Almighty Creator of the World, and the mercifull Saviour of mankind, who art above our thoughts, and excellest the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the highest Angels, thou art greatly to be feared in the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:109636:97"/>of thy Saints, and to be had in reverence of all those that are round about thee, I most humbly desire leave to joyn my self with all those Holy ones, to worship thy most glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Majesty, to express the due sense I have of all thy benefits (by paying thee my most thankfull Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments for them) to make thee the best oblation I am able, and devote my self entirely to thy obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, since thou hast graciously en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined me to go into thine House, and there to set forth thy praise, to declare thy loving kindness, to resign my self to thy Will, to recommend my self to thy Wisdom, to submit to thy Government, to approve the Justice and Goodness of all thy Laws, to profess that I am thy Servant, to renounce all thy Enemies, and to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie my continued purpose to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee against all the Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the World, the Flesh and the Devil: Be pleased, good Lord, to pardon all my former failings, and at this time to accept my Holy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and inspire me from above
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:109636:97"/>that I may chearfully perform all these acts of Devotion to thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majesty, and vouchsafe more fully to inform me in my duty, to correct and amend what is amiss in me, to encourage and strengthen my good resolutions, and to assist me in all well-doing: Fill me with a great love to thee and my Blessed Saviour, to thy Holy Word and to all Holy Duties to Christian People every where, and to all mankind. Perfect me in Wisdom, in Holiness, and in Goodness, by all thy Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, by all thy Mercies, by all thy Chastisements, and by all my Prayers, Praises, and Thanksgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to thee the Father of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: Make me such as thou canst Love and Delight in and reward at the great day of the Lord Jesus.</p>
               <p>At my Entrance into the Church.</p>
               <p>I will come into thine House, O Lord, even upon the multitude of thy mercies, and in thy fear will I Worship towards thy Holy Temple.</p>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:109636:98"/>
               <p>When in my Pew.</p>
               <p>Let the words of my mouth and the Meditation of my heart, be now and always acceptable in thy sight, O Lord, my Strength and my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
               <p>For the Exercise of my Thoughts, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Minister begins to Officiate and to avoid that silly Custom of observing fashions in the Church, I meditate on the Psalms appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be then read.</p>
               <p>When the Minister has named the Text, I carefully attend to,
<list>
                     <item>1. The Explication or meaning of the Words.</item>
                     <item>2. The Divisions and Heads of the discourse.</item>
                     <item>3. The Reasons and Arguments for, and against any matter.</item>
                     <item>4. The Places of Scripture quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:109636:98"/>
               <p>Which I endeavour to retain in memory, as proper for my Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when I am come from Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>As soon as the Sermon is ended, I use this short Prayer.</head>
               <p>GRant, O Lord, that the Words which I have now heard with my outward Ears, may be by thy Grace so grafted inwardly in my heart, that it may bring forth in me the fruit of good living, to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory of thy Holy Name.</p>
               <p>When that part of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is dismiss'd, as does not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, I seat my self as near the Communion-Table as I can conveniently, being willing to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve and comply with all that's per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Devotions for the Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For my Meditation untill the Minister begins the Offertory, I make use of that Exhortation of the Church,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:109636:99"/>(repeated by the Minister at the time of the celebration of the Communion) in manner following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Exhortation.</head>
               <p>YE that mind to come to the holy Communion of the Body and Blood of our Saviour Christ, must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider how St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth all persons diligently to <hi>try and examin</hi> themselves before they presume to eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup: for as the Benefit is great, if with a true pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Heart and lively Faith we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that holy Sacrament, for then we spiritually eat the Flesh of Christ, and drink his Blood; then we dwell in Christ, and Christ in us; we are one with Christ, and Christ with us; so is the danger great, if we receive the same unworthily, for then we are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Body and Blood of Christ our Saviour, we eat and drink our own Damnation, not considering the Lord's Body, we kindle God's Wrath against us, we provoke him to plague us with
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:109636:99"/>diverse and sundry kinds of Death: Judge therefore your selves, Brethren, that you be not judg'd of the Lord; repent you truly of your sins past, have a lively and stedfast Faith in Christ our Saviour, amend your Lives, and be in perfect Charity with all men, so shall ye be meet partakers of those holy My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries.</p>
               <p>O Lord, truly I am thy Servant, I am thy Servant, I am sensible I am not my own, for I am bought with a great Price, and therefore ought to glorifie God in my body, and in my spirit, which are God's. And, good Lord, assist me (as one that names the Name of Christ) to depart from all Iniquity.</p>
               <p>And above all things, ye must give most humble and hearty Thanks to God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghost, for the Redemption of the World by the Death and Passion of our Saviour Christ, both God and Man, who did humble himself even to the Death upon the Cross, for us miserable
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:109636:100"/>sinners; who lay in <hi>darkness▪</hi> and the <hi>shadow of Death,</hi> that he might make us the Children of God, and exalt us to Everlasting Life.</p>
               <p>WHat shall I render unto the Lord for all his Benefits towards me, especially for this, that he hath not spar'd his own <hi>Son,</hi> but deliver'd him up for us all?</p>
               <p>And to the end that we should al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways remember the exceeding great love of our Master and only Saviour Jesus Christ, thus dying for us, and the innumerable Benefits which by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood-shedding he hath obtained to us, he hath instituted and ordained holy Mysteries, as Pledges of his Love, and for a continual remembrance of his Death, to our great and endless Comfort.</p>
               <p>TO him therefore, with the Father and the Holy Ghost, do I give (as I am most bounden) continual Thanks, submitting my self wholly to his holy Will and Pleasure, and study<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:109636:100"/>to serve him in true Holiness and Righteousness all the days of my Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>At giving Alms.</head>
               <p>O Let this Alms be an Odour of a sweet smell, a Sacrifice accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and well-pleasing unto thee, by Jesus Christ.</p>
               <p>Immediately before I go to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion-Table.</p>
               <p>I Do not presume to come to this thy Table, O merciful Lord, trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in my own Righteousness, but in thy manifold and great Mercies: I am not worthy so much as to gather up the Crumbs under thy Table; but thou art the same Lord, whose Property is always to have mercy: Grant me therefore, gracious Lord, so to eat the Flesh of thy dear Son Jesus Christ, and to drink his Blood, that my sinful Body may be made clean by his Body, and my Soul washed through his most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood, and that I may evermore dwell in him, and he in me.</p>
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:109636:101"/>
               <p>At the Table, before I kneel down to receive I expostulate with my self thus:</p>
               <p>Do I truly and earnestly repent me of my Sins? Am I in Love and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with my Neighbour? And do I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to lead a new life, following the Commandments of God, and walking from henceforth in his holy Laws?</p>
               <p>Being able to return the Answer of a good Conscience;</p>
               <p>Then I will draw near with Faith, and take this holy Sacrament to my Comfort, and make my humble Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession to Almighty God.</p>
               <p>Then meekly kneeling at the Table,</p>
               <p>Lord, I am not worthy that thou shouldst come under my Roof.</p>
               <p>I have sinned, what shall I do unto thee, O thou Preserver of Men?</p>
               <p>Here I recollect some of my greatest Sins.</p>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:109636:101"/>
               <p>If thou, Lord, shouldst be extream, to mark what is done amiss, O Lord, who may abide it?</p>
               <p>But with the Lord there is mercy, and with him there is plenteous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>Behold, O Lord, thy beloved Son, in whom thou art well pleased.</p>
               <p>Hearken to the Cry of his Blood, which speaketh better things than that of <hi>Abel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By his Agony and bloody Sweat, by his Cross and Passion, good Lord, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me.</p>
               <p>O Lamb of God, which takest away the Sins of the World, grant me thy Peace.</p>
               <p>O Lamb of God, which takest away the Sins of the World, have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me.</p>
               <p>Immediately before receiving;</p>
               <p>Thou hast said, that he that eateth thy Flesh, and drinketh thy Blood hath Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>Behold the Servant of the Lord: be it unto me according to thy Word.</p>
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:109636:102"/>
               <p>At the receiving of the Bread.</p>
               <p>By thy Crucified Body, deliver me from this Body of Death.</p>
               <p>At the receiving of the Cup.</p>
               <p>O let this Blood of thine purge my Conscience from dead Works, to serve the Living God.</p>
               <p>Lord, if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean.</p>
               <p>O touch me, and say, <hi>I will thou be clean.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After Receiving.</p>
               <p>What shall I render unto the Lord for all the Benefits that he hath done unto me?</p>
               <p>I will take the Cup of Salvation, and will call upon the Name of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Worthy is the Lamb that was slain to receive Power, and Riches, and Wisdom, and Strength, and Honour, and Glory, and Blessing: Therefore Blessing, Honour, Glory and Power be
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:109636:102"/>to him that sitteth upon the Throne, and to the Lamb, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Going from the Table to my Pew:</p>
               <p>I have sworn, and am stedfastly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to keep thy Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>O hold thou up my Goings in thy Paths, that my Footsteps slip not.</p>
               <p>When come to my Pew, I use this</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Thanksgiving.</head>
               <p>O Thou Fountain of all Goodness! from whom every good and perfect Gift cometh, and to whom all Honour and Glory should be returned, I desire with all the most fervent and inflamed Affections of a grateful heart, to bless and praise thee, for those in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>estimable Mercies thou hast vouchsaf'd me: Lord, what is Man, that thou shouldst so regard him, as to send thy beloved Son to suffer such bitter things for him? But, Lord, what am I, the
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:109636:103"/>worst of Men, that I should have any part in this Atonement, who have so often despis'd him and his Sufferings? O the heighth and depth of this Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of thine, that art pleased to admit me to the renewing of that Covenant with thee which I have so often and so perversely broken! That I, who am not worthy of that daily Bread which sustains the Body, should be made Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of this Bread of Life, which nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risheth the Soul, and that the God of all Purity should vouchsafe to unite himself to so polluted a Wretch! O my God, suffer me no more, I beseech thee, to turn thy Grace into Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, to make thy Mercy an occasion of Security, but let this unspeakable love of thine constrain me to Obedience, that since my blessed Lord hath dy'd for me, I may no longer live unto my self, but to him. O Lord, I know there is no Concord between Christ and <hi>Belial,</hi> therefore since he hath now been pleas'd to enter my Heart, O let me never permit any Lust to chase him thence, but let him that hath so dearly bought me still keep possession of me,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:109636:103"/>and let nothing ever take me out of his hand. To this end be thou graciously pleased to watch over me, and defend me from all Assaults of my spiritual Enemies, but especially deliver me from my self, from the Treachery of my own Heart, which is too willing to yield it self a Prey; and where thou seest I am either by Nature or Custom most weak, there do thou, I beseech thee, magnifie thy power in my preservation; <hi>[here I mention my most dangerous Temptations]</hi> and, Lord, let my Saviour's Sufferings for my Sins, and the Vows I have now made against them, never depart from my Mind, but let the remembrance of the one enable me to perform the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that I may never make Truce with those Lusts which nailed his Hands, pierced his Sides, and made his Soul heavy to the Death; but that having now anew listed my self under his Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, I may fight manfully, and follow the Captain of my Salvation, even thro' a Sea of Blood. Lord, lift up my hands that hang down, and my feeble knees, that I faint not in this Warfare: O be thou my strength, who am not able of
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:109636:104"/>my self to struggle with the flightest Temptations. How often have I turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my back in the day of Battel! how many of these sacramental Vows have I violated! and, Lord, I have still the same unconstant deceitful Heart to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray me to the breach of this. O thou who art <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen,</hi> in whom there is no shadow of Change, communicate to me, I beseech thee, such a stability of Mind, that I may no more thus start aside, like a broken Bow, but that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my Heart whole with thee, I may continue stedfast in thy Covenant, that not one good Purpose which thy Spirit hath raised in me this day may vanish, as so many formerly have done, but that they may bring forth unto Life-eternal. Grant this, O merciful Father, through the Merits and Mediation of my Crucified Saviour.</p>
               <p>Whilst others are Communicating, I reflect on my Baptismal Vow, and consider how nearly I am concern'd in keeping this Vow of Baptism, and that</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1st,</hi> In respect of Justice; and</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> In respect of Advantage and Benefit.</p>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:109636:104"/>
               <p>That I am in Justice bound to it, I conclude it is a Promise, and that Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice requires of every man the keeping of his Promise; but then this is, of all other Promises, the most solemn and binding, for it is a Vow, that is, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise made to God; and therefore I am not only unjust, but forsworn, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I break any part of it.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Secondly,</hi> I am also highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to keep it, in respect of my own benefit; for <hi>Baptism</hi> enters me into Covenant with God: Now a Covenant is made up of two parts, that is, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing promised by the one Party, and something by the other of the Parties that make the Covenant; and if one of them break his part of the Covenant, that is, perform not what he has agreed to, he can in no reason look that the other should make good his. And so it is here: God doth indeed promise, that I shall be a Member of Christ, a Child of God, and an Inheriter of the Kingdom of Heaven, and that is His part of the Covenant; but then I also undertake to perform the several things contain'd in this Vow of Baptism, and
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:109636:105"/>that is my part of it; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less indeed I do perform them, God is not ty'd to make good his, and so forfeit all these precious benefits and advantages: I am left in that natural and miserable state of mine, a Child of Wrath an Enemy to God, and an Heir of Eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>As soon as the Communion service is ended, and the Blessing given, I Conclude with this short Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</head>
               <p>O God, I have now once more solemnly renewed my baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal vow, and have again underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to perform the several things contained therein, with an assurance of thine eternal favour ever. And now what can be the pleasure that any or all sins can afford me, that can make me the least degree of recompence for the loss of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Grace here, and the loss of my own Soul hereafter. O let me not be overcome by the least
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:109636:105"/>Temptation, tho' the whole World should be secur'd to me upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of it: Suffer me not to say as <hi>Lot</hi> did of <hi>Zoar,</hi> Is it not a little one? but grant that I may consider that whatever it is, I have in my Baptism vowed against it, and that be it never so little, it draws a great one at the heels of it, no less than that of being forsworn, which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever commits, thou hast declared not to hold him guiltless? Grant this, O Lord, for the sake of Jesus Christ, my blessed Lord and Saviour.</p>
               <p>Going out of the Church.</p>
               <p>One day in thy Court is better than a Thousand.</p>
               <p>I had rather be a door-keeper in the House of my God, than to dwell in the Tents of Ungodliness.</p>
               <p>After I am come from Church, I immediately enter in writing what I can remember of the Sermon, and then employ as much time as I can
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:109636:106"/>conveniently in digesting what I have heard.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>After which I repeat with great at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention the following Prayer.</head>
               <p>I Adore thee, again Lord of Life and Glory, I acknowledge my depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on thee; I thank thee for thy Mercies, which thou never ceasest to heap upon me: Accept, I beseech thee, of that dedication I have made of the Soul and Body, with Praises and Thanksgivings unto thee, in the publick Congregation: be mercifull to all my sins, and endue me with the Grace of thy holy spirit to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me to present my self when I appear again before thee, a more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and devout Sacrifice unto thee; stedfastly resolved and chearfully dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>osed, in every thing to be order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thy will, for which end be pleased to settle and root in my heart a stronger belief of thy Holy Gospel, and to six my Thoughts and Affections upon that unseen Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:109636:106"/>and Bliss where our Saviour is, that nothing here below may either allure or fright me from my duty, nor ever make me remiss or neglect in it, but I may be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of good Works, fervent in spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, serving my Lord, from whom I expect the reward of an Immortal Inheritance: Preserve in me always a Religious sense of thee, and make me now so sober and thankfull a parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the refreshments of my Body, that they may not damp the Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Soul, but I may rather return to Worship thee with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Chearfullness, and Gladness of heart, after thou hast added the good things of this World, to those of the other, according to thy abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Love in Christ Jesus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:109636:107"/>
               <p>I allow of no Worldly matters to be discoursed of at Dinner or at any other time of such solemn days, unless an Absolute Necessity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervene.</p>
               <p>After dinner (being conveniently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd) I again look over the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I took of the morning Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, with which together with the following Prayers, I employ my thoughts until Church time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>This Prayer immediately before I go to Church in the afternoon.</head>
               <p>O God, who art rich in mercy to all that call upon thee, and hast bid us pray without ceasing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce evermore, in obedience to thy Commands, and encouraged by the goodness of thy nature, thy gracious invitations, thy most precious promises and the long Experience that I and others have had of thy bounty, I am bold again to approach into thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, to renew my request unto thee,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:109636:107"/>to bless thy Holy Name, to make profession of my Love to thee, and readiness in all things to obey thee, quicken my thoughts and affections to a free and joyfull attendance on thee in all Holy duties, that no dullness or weariness seize on my spirit, but such a fervent Love to thee may pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess my heart, as may render all the Employments of Religion my delight, and the doing thy Will, both now and always my greatest pleasure: and pass by, I most humbly beseech thee, all my unwilling indispositions, accept of such service as I am able to render thee, and dispose me by all my addresses to thee, to be more Circumspect and Watchfull, more Diligent and Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious, more Forward and Zealous in the Performance of every part of my duty, that being led by thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel, Govern'd by thy Spirit, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd by thy Gracious Providence, I may at last be admitted into the Company of the Blessed; there to perfect my Prayers and Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to receive the reward of Patient Continuance in well-doing,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:109636:108"/>thro' Jesus Christ, whose Grace be with my Spirit. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>At Church I observe the same directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as in the morning.</head>
               <head type="sub">After I am come from Church, I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter down in writing (as in the morning) what I can remember of this Afternoon Sermon, which I carefully meditate on, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately repeat the following Prayer.</head>
               <p>I Acknowledge thy manifold Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, O Lord, which are renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon me every moment; I owe my Life continually to thee, with all the Comforts of it, if I had no more to thank thee for, but the mercies of this day, they are so many and so great, that I could never thank thee enough for them, thou takest care of my Body and of my Soul, thou feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est me at thy House, and at my own, thou lettest me taste of the Bread of Life, which came down from Heaven; besides the many supports and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshments which thou affordest for this natural Life, several of thy Creatures
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:109636:108"/>lose their lives to preserve mine; and thy dear Son hath not thought it too much to lay down his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Life for my sake; thou speakest to me, and givest me leave to speak to thee: Thou instructest me in my duty, and hast made these things my duty, which are rearly my happiness. Thou engagest me to do my self good here, by promising a greater good hereafter: I praise, I thank thee, and will be ever speaking of thee, and it is a new favour that I may thus praise and bless thee, both in the Assembly of thy people, and in my own retirements: O give me an heart to delight in it, and in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy duties of a Christian Life; that obeying thy Holy Gospel in all things, and being never weary in well-doing, I may find thy unwearied Goodness extending it self to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Bliss and Life, through Jesus Christ. O Blessed Jesus, that thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Laws may be more deeply engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on my heart: O that every truth I have learnt this day may be so faithfully preserved and kept in
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:109636:109"/>mind, as to become the rule of my Life, or the ground of my hope, and a powerful motive to universal and uniform Obedience to the End of my days: O that the remainder of my days may be the better for this day, and the Holy rest we observe here on Earth, may be a beginning of that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal rest which we wait for at the second coming. <hi>Amen.</hi> Come Lord Jesus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>A Private walk (after the service of the Church is over) either in the fields or ones own Garden, if the season of the year will permit, or a visit to a Friend, if our thoughts and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses do not at all tend to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of so holy a day, I think may reasonably be allowed.</p>
               <p>Humane Nature is not capable of performing an uninterrupted Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and consequently Justifiable in the moderate use of ease and refreshment.</p>
               <p>For all other Occasions, I refer my self to my ordinary Devotions.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:109636:109"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>